<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Pope's cabinet unlocked, or, A catalogue of all the popes indulgences belonging to the order of S. Mary together with a list of all the indulgences daily, yearly, and for ever, to be had at Rome, S. James of Galatia in Compostella, Jerusalem and all places in the Holy Land / written in Italian by Fr. Ancangelo Tortello of the said order of S. Mary : and now translated into English by John Sidway late seminary priest, but now of the reformed religion and vicar of selling in Kent and one of the discoverers of the horrid popish plot, with the cause of his conversion : whereunto is added an appendix by the translator in which the grounds and foundation of the said indulgences being themselves apparently proved to be meer cheats : and also shewing that the Church of Rome doth lay the chief basis of their religion on indulgences : dedicated to the right honourable the Earl of Shaftsbury.</title>
            <author>Tortello, Arcangelo.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 232 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94760</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1943</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3021</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13448378</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13448378</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152745</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94760)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152745)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 478:22 or 2318:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Pope's cabinet unlocked, or, A catalogue of all the popes indulgences belonging to the order of S. Mary together with a list of all the indulgences daily, yearly, and for ever, to be had at Rome, S. James of Galatia in Compostella, Jerusalem and all places in the Holy Land / written in Italian by Fr. Ancangelo Tortello of the said order of S. Mary : and now translated into English by John Sidway late seminary priest, but now of the reformed religion and vicar of selling in Kent and one of the discoverers of the horrid popish plot, with the cause of his conversion : whereunto is added an appendix by the translator in which the grounds and foundation of the said indulgences being themselves apparently proved to be meer cheats : and also shewing that the Church of Rome doth lay the chief basis of their religion on indulgences : dedicated to the right honourable the Earl of Shaftsbury.</title>
                  <author>Tortello, Arcangelo.</author>
                  <author>Sidway, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 77 (i.e. 76) p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Isaac Cleve at the Star next to Serjeants-Inn in Chancery-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Item at reel 2318:23 incorrectly identified as Wing T1943aA.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in Library of Congress and Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:152745:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Printed for Isaac Cleave at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſigne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Starr next to Searjants Jnn in Chancery Lane</head>
                  <figDesc>Engraved frontispiece showing the devil whispering into the ear of the Pope and his Cardinals whilst a penitent buys absolution, handing over a bag of coins in exchange for a Papal indulgence.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152745:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Pope's Cabinet UNLOCKED: OR, A CATALOGUE Of all the POPES INDULGENCES Belonging to the Order of S. <hi>Mary,</hi> TOGETHER With a Liſt of all the <hi>Indulgences</hi> daily, yearly, and for ever, to be had at <hi>Rome,</hi> S. <hi>James</hi> of <hi>Galatia</hi> in <hi>Compoſtella, Jeruſalem,</hi> and all places in the Holy Land.</p>
            <p>Written in <hi>Italian</hi> by <hi>Fr. Arcangelo Tortello,</hi> of the ſaid Order of S. <hi>Mary:</hi> And now Tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>John Sidway,</hi> late Seminary Prieſt, but now of the Reformed Religion, and Vicar of <hi>Selling</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> and one of the Diſcoverers of the horrid Popiſh Plot, with the Cauſe of his Converſion.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is added an APPENDIX by the Tranſlator, in which the grounds and foundation of the ſaid <hi>Indulgences</hi> being examined, are utterly overthrown, and by conſequence <hi>Indulgences</hi> themſelves apparently proved to be meer Cheats. And alſo ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth lay the chief Baſis of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion on <hi>Indulgences.</hi> Dedicated to the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Iſaac Cleve</hi> at the Star next to <hi>Serjeants-Inn</hi> in <hi>Chancery-Lane.</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152745:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152745:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE ANTHONY EARL of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> Baron <hi>Aſhly</hi> of <hi>Winbourne S. Giles,</hi> Lord <hi>Cooper</hi> of <hi>Pawlet, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE ſignal Favours received from your Honour, and the confidence I have of your Lordſhips Endeavours to conſerve Religion in its true purity, imboldeneth me to preſent you with this worthleſs Preſent, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for you ever ſince it was in the confuſed Maſs of my thoughts; which if your Lordſhip pleaſe to peruſe, and receive into Protection, and the pious Reader reap advantage by my intendment, my Deſign hath ſucceeded to my wiſh. The matter contained in the Tranſlation is a Catalogue of the Popes Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, or Inventory of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Treaſure; which Treaſure, or Indulgences, being grounded upon meer Fictions, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently at beſt but Cheats, I have in my Appendix endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to deſtroy, overthrowing the very Ground-works, both by Scripture and Fathers, whereupon they are founded. My De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign herein is to unmask this grand Deceit of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, conceiving that they that truſt to the ſaid Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, rely on worſe than Reeds, being thereby expoſed to
<pb facs="tcp:152745:3"/>the greateſt danger; and meerly guld, not onely of their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, but their Expectations. Thus humbly craving your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Pardon for this my boldneſs; beſeeching God daily to increaſe that ardent affection you bear to Religion; and that his Grace and Goodneſs may always ſupply you with meet gifts and Priviledges to do him Service, and increaſe your Comforts here and hereafter, I adventure to ſubſcribe, and eſteem my ſelf happy, in the honour of being</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>My Lord, Your Lordſhips moſt humble and moſt devoted Servant,</hi> JOH. SIDWAY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:152745:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHatſoever thou art, great is the benefit that thou mayeſt receive by this little Book. Art thou a <hi>Romaniſt,</hi> knowing thy Religion to be grounded in all Controverted Points upon thoſe Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, thou mayeſt by the Grace of God (ſeeing them here overthrown) be brought to relinquiſh thy Erroneous O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions. Art thou a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> or any other diſſenting from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> here thou mayeſt diſcover a great part of the <hi>Roman Eccleſinſtick Policy;</hi> and by what means ſuch abſurd Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents as are held in the Roman Church are introduced into the good Opinion of the people, and admitted into their Faith, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs not to the end they may by thee be imitated, but abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and avoided. Would'ſt thou know by what means they came to ſo many Religious Orders, and why ſo many enter (as they call it) into Religion? 'tis becauſe of the many and great Indulgences which they are poſſeſt with a belief they obtain thereby. Would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou know wherefore they invocate and adore Saints, the Hoſt, the Crucifix, Holy Relicks and Images, 'tis becauſe of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences. Wouldeſt thou know the reaſon of their ſtrict ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of theſe and other their Churches Ceremonies, their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of one Church and Altar before another, and of all their Pilgrimages? 'tis becauſe of Indulgences. In fine, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Controverted betwixt the <hi>Roman</hi> and other Churches, but, leſt the ſame ſhould be utterly overthrown, they are ſome way un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derpropped by Indulgences: which although but meer Cheats, and therefore at beſt but rotten Poſts, yet ſince the people are brought to have ſo good an Opinion of them, ſerve as moſt itable and firm Pillars. In the overthrowing whereof, though I have uſed much the Fathers, yet 'tis not with an Opinion they are more infallible
<pb facs="tcp:152745:4"/>than others, or that we are to regard any more their Teſtimony, but becauſe (dealing with the <hi>Romaniſts</hi>) I deal with an unreaſonable people, who believe no other, no not ſo much as the holy Scriptures, unleſs as the Fathers expound them, I have here produced them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other Teſtimonies. For my part I was brought up, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued until about three years ſince, in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in which I was of no ſmall repute and eſteem, but Conſcience did ſo accuſe and torment me, being Conſcious to my ſelf of ſo many <hi>grand Abſurdities, groſs Idolatries,</hi> and <hi>ſuperſtitious Practices,</hi> which I found I muſt of neceſſity be guilty of dayly, continuing therein, that utterly relinquiſhing that of <hi>Rome,</hi> I adjoyned with the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> in my coming unto which, although I was put to beat out the way as it were through Fire, and have been ſince by many thereof very hardly dealt withal, which I pray God forgive, I have receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the greateſt joy in Spirit and Conſolation in Conſcience imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable; verily believing, That amongſt all eſtabliſhed Churches in the whole Univerſe, which I have ſeen, and bleſſed be God I have ſeen all, or moſt, that there is not any nearer to Scripture and Primitive Practice, than is the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and rather than I would return to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> admit my ſelf, or condeſcend to maintain any one point of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> peculiar Doctrine, there is not a Torment ſo great, nor a Death ſo grievous, which I would not gladly ſuffer. The ſaid Indulgences amongſt other things were one reaſon of my relinquiſhing of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed been at moſt of the places where the ſaid Indulgences are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and know the enſuing Catalogue to agree with the Records and Reports of each place, and conceiving that thoſe that are cured of a dangerous Malady ought, not to conceal the means conducing thereunto, from thoſe that either are or may be ſick of the ſame Diſeaſe, I have thought meet to publiſh the ſame to the World, which if kindly accepted, may induce me to many other Works of the like kind, and of ſhewing my ſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy very Well-wiſher, Joh. Sidway.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152745:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE AUTHOR'S EPISTLE DEDICATORY.</head>
            <head type="sub">To my illuſtrious and venerable Brothers and Siſters of the Company of the moſt glorious Virgin.</head>
            <p>BY how much the more I know my ſelf obliged in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and in particular to your moſt noble Country, and the more I go about accuſing my ſelf a Debtor for ſo many Favours and Benefits in the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually received, ſo much the leſs I have always hitherto found my ſelf in a Capacity to expreſs that great and inward deſire I have to do ſome Act that may be grateful to you; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering with my ſelf I ought to give you ſome little ſign of my good Will, and of my great regard and good Remembrance of you; and that the longer I defer it, the more it ought to anſwer the debt I owe: Newly returned from his Holineſs's the Popes Pallace, and fearing I might ſeem to be like the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Servant, in the Goſpel, who hid the Talent received at the Courteſie of his Patron, I here preſent you with a Liſt, (I there obtained) of the publick Treaſure, that although it be yet ſo much unknown in many other Cities, it may be now known to you, who are the holy Company of our habit, given by the ever Virgin, the Mother of the Son of God; the which you accepting, as I hope you will, and Conjure you that ye ſo do, you have all the Indulgences, may be gained by the
<pb facs="tcp:152745:5"/>Brothers and Siſters of our Company, in this little Book; which giving to you, together I dedicate and conſecrate to you, beſeeching you to place this laudable Inſcription in our Church of the Servants, accompanying the ſame to the Altar of the moſt holy Crucifix with your Society; to the end that in Life and in Death you may obtain a double Treaſure, and Patronage, and ſo Precious as theſe two are; the which joyntly in the dangerous Navigation of this world, the one will be the Ship, and the other the Star, to the port of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. The gift is not ſmall becauſe it is a gift Spiritual; neither ought the reſpect to be ſmall that is had thereto, in regard of the great Benefit that may accrue thereby. And for a Credit and truth of what is therein contained, I have cauſed the ſame to be confirmed with the great Seal of our Office, and have ſubſcribed the ſame with mine own hand. Dated at <hi>Florence</hi> in our Convent <hi>della Nonciata,</hi> the ninth day of <hi>February,</hi> 1599.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Fr. Arcangelo Tortello.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152745:5"/>
            <head>The Treaſure of the Brothers and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Holy Order of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Saint <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>CLASSE I.</hi> The Indulgences which they obtain by reaſon of the Habit of the Servants of our LADY.</head>
               <p>TO them that receive the Habit of the Servants, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> the Eighth granted that the Prior General, or any other conſtituted by him, might abſolve any, whether He or She that ſhould have that Habit, not only at his or her Entrance, but at any time whenſoever there ſhould be need, from any ſin or Cenſure whatſoever.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Siſto</hi> the Fourth granted a Plenary Indulgence to any when they received the Habit of the Servants.</p>
               <p>To thoſe inveſted with the Habit of the Servants, <hi>Innocent</hi> the Eighth, <hi>Alexander</hi> the Fourth, <hi>Benedict</hi> the Eleventh, and other Popes their Succeſſors, granted, that once in their life time, and once in their death, they ſhould obtain a plenary Indulgence of all their ſins.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Siſto</hi> the Fourth ſaid, that they ſhould obtain a Plenary Indulgence when they dyed and wanted a Confeſſor, becauſe they dyed in the ſtate of grace.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth granted to any one inveſted with the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of the Servants, that ſhould ſay the ſeven penitential Pſalms once over, or five <hi>Pater-noſter's</hi> and five <hi>Ave Maria's</hi> before an Altar of the Church where he or ſhe ſhould reſide, that he or ſhe that ſaid the ſame, ſhould thereby releaſe any one Soul out of Purgatory, what Soul the party that ſaith the ſame pleaſeth.</p>
               <p>To thoſe which to the honour of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:152745:6"/>ſhall devoutly kiſs the Habit of one of the Servants, <hi>John</hi> the twenty third hath given five years, and five Quarantenes (one of which is forty days ſpace) of Indulgence.</p>
               <p>To thoſe which ſhall ſerve with the Habit under the Servants, <hi>Clement</hi> the Fourth, <hi>Nicholas</hi> the Third, and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the Fifth, granted a forgiveneſs of the third part of their ſins; and <hi>Siſto</hi> the Fourth, and <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth granted them a plenary Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
               <p>To thoſe inveſted with the Habit of the Servants, and ſhall ſay five <hi>Pater-noſter's,</hi> and five <hi>Ave-Maria's, Paul</hi> the ſecond hath granted all the Indulgences which are at any time within or without <hi>Rome,</hi> as well as to thoſe that viſit the Holy Churches, where they are to be obtained.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth hath granted, that ſaying five <hi>Pater-noſter's,</hi> and five <hi>Ave-Maria's,</hi> and at the end of each <hi>Pater-noſter</hi> and <hi>Ave-Maria,</hi> one <hi>Gloria Patri,</hi> all entire; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another <hi>Pater-noſter</hi> and <hi>Ave-Maria</hi> ſingly, with the <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Patri, &amp;c.</hi> That is to ſay in the whole, ſix <hi>Pater-noſter's,</hi> ſix <hi>Ave-Maria's,</hi> and ſix <hi>Gloria Patri's;</hi> five whereof with an intention to gain the Indulgence, and one for his Holineſs the Pope, they gain and obtain all the Indulgences in the Stations at <hi>Rome,</hi> at St. <hi>James</hi> of <hi>Galitia</hi> in <hi>Compoſtella,</hi> and at <hi>Jerufalem,</hi> and other places in the Holy Land: And moreover this Pope hath ſaid, that in whatſoever hour of the day or of the night they will, or in whatſoever place they will, to wit, in the Choire, or in the Church, or in the Cloyſter, or in the Cell, if any can ſay the ſaid <hi>Pater-noſter's, Ave-Maria's,</hi> and <hi>Gloria Patri's, &amp;c.</hi> they ſhall obtain the Indulgences.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>CLASSE II.</hi> The Indulgences at the Holy City of <hi>Rome,</hi> which are gained not only by devout Pilgrims, and ſuch others, as viſit the ſacred places where they are to be obtained, but alſo by the Brothers and Siſters of the Servants of our Lady.</head>
               <p>IN the famous City of <hi>Rome</hi> where commonly reſideth the Pope, the Vicar of Jeſus Chriſt, the place where ſo many Saints and Sainteſſes have been martyred, and ſanctified the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152745:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>ground with their moſt holy blood, there is not a Church in which there is not any day moſt great Indulgences; but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt there are ſeven called for their Excellency, <hi>The Seven Churches of Rome,</hi> the which are every day very devoutly, with great adorations, by great numbers of people viſited; and as they have been, ſo they are daily by his Holineſs the Pope, priviledged and benefitted.</p>
               <p>The firſt of the Seven Churches is the Church of Saint <hi>John Lateran,</hi> the which was built by the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and dedicated by St. <hi>Silveſter</hi> the Pope, who at its dedication gave ſo many Indulgences thereto, that is, to thoſe that devoutly vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit the ſame, that none can number them, but only God.</p>
               <p>Firſt at the great Altar they gain an Indulgence of forty eight years, and of forty eight times forty days ſpace, and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over a forgiveneſs of the third part of their ſins.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Silveſter</hi> gave to whoſoever ſhould come to viſit this Church, at what time of the year ſoever he came, a full remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all his ſins.</p>
               <p>In this Church of S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> where an Image viſibly and miraculouſly appeared when S. <hi>Silveſter</hi> conſecrated the ſame, there is full remiſſion of all their ſins.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> hath ſaid, that whoſoever comes for Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on's ſake to viſit the Church of S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> ſhall be clean abſolved from all manner of ſin.</p>
               <p>Within this Church there is a Chappel of S. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> into which no Woman is permitted to enter, and there alſo they have full remiſſion of all their ſins.</p>
               <p>In the Chappel of S. <hi>Laurence,</hi> called <hi>Sancta Sanctorum,</hi> (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Women alſo are not permitted to enter) there is painted an Image of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, at which they have an Indulgence of twelve years, and full remiſſion of all their ſins.</p>
               <p>Over the Altar Papal are reſerved the Heads of S. <hi>Peter</hi> and S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and every time they ſhew them, to them that inhabit in and about <hi>Rome</hi> there are three thouſand years of Indulgenee; but to thoſe that live a conſiderable diſtance from <hi>Rome,</hi> as a days journey, ſix thouſand years; and to thoſe that come from a far Country, there is given an Indulgence of twelve thouſand years, and of twelve thouſand times forty days ſpace, and moreover a forgiveneſs of the third part of their ſins.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152745:7"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152745:7"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:152745:8"/>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>John Lateran</hi> there is a Chappel between the Oratory and Baptiſtory, in which every day they have full remiſſion of all their ſins.</p>
               <p>Moreover, near to this Chappel is the Ladder of <hi>Pilate</hi>'s Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, by the which Chriſt our Lord was faſtened to the Pillar; the Ladder hath twenty eight ſteps or rounds, and whoſoever goeth up the ſame, for every ſtep he aſcends thereof, he hath nine years, and nine times forty days ſpace of Indulgence, and alſo the forgiveneſs of the third part of his ſins.</p>
               <p>And in the Head of this Church is a Chappel in which are the Ark of the Teſtament, the Rod of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and the Table upon which Chriſt ſupped with the Diſciples; and there are very many Indulgences.</p>
               <p>In this Church of S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> at the Creation of every Pope, there is (if they ſhew the holy Vault) a plenary Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
               <p>The ſecond of the ſeven Churches, is the Church of Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> where at preſent is the Seat Apoſtolick: At this Church any day they gain an Indulgence of ſix thouſand forty eight years, and likewiſe of ſix thouſand forty eight times forty days ſpace, and moreover a forgiveneſs of the third part of their ſins.</p>
               <p>Alſo in the Feaſt of the Annunciation of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> there is a thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
               <p>Alſo from the ſaid Feaſt until the firſt day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> there is an Indulgence of twelve thouſand years, and of twelve thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times forty days ſpace; and moreover, to thoſe that gain the Indulgence a forgiveneſs of the third part of all their ſins.</p>
               <p>Alſo whoſoever devoutly aſcends the ſteps or ſtairs of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> there are granted him by <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth, for every ſtep or ſtair he aſcends, ſeven years Indulgence.</p>
               <p>At every Altar alſo of the <hi>Church</hi> of S. <hi>Peter</hi> there is an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence of eighteen thouſand years; and amongſt the reſt, the ſeven principal Altars are priviledged with greater Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences.</p>
               <p>At the Feaſt of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> or the Feaſts of any of the ſaid Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, or the Feaſt of <hi>All Saints,</hi> or the Feaſt following, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences are all doubled.</p>
               <p>In the ſaid <hi>Church</hi> when they ſhew the Holy Vault, which for the moſt part is in the Holy Week, <hi>Eaſter-day, Aſcenſion-day,</hi> and the <hi>Sunday</hi> before St. <hi>Anthony Abbot;</hi> beſides thoſe that follow,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152745:8"/>there is an Indulgence to Strangers of twelve thouſand years; to thoſe that live near <hi>Rome</hi> of ſix thouſand years; and to thoſe that are Inhabitants in <hi>Rome</hi> of three thouſand years, and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over to each, of as many times forty days ſpace; and likewiſe all have the forgiveneſs of the third part of their Sins.</p>
               <p>Moreover in this Church of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> they have every day, from Aſcenſion to the end of the Calends of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> eighteen thouſand years Indulgence; and from the Annunciation to the end of the ſaid Calends, they gain an Indulgence of twelve thouſand years, and alſo of twelve thouſand times forty days ſpace, and moreover a forgiveneſs of the third part of their Sins.</p>
               <p>And in the ſaid Church at the Papal Chappel, they have every day a Plenary Remiſſion of their Sins.</p>
               <p>The third of the ſeven Churches of <hi>Rome</hi> is the Church of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in the which any day they gain an Indulgence of ſix thouſand forty eight years, and likewiſe of ſix thouſand forty eight Quarantenes, (every of which is forty days ſpace) and moreover the forgiveneſs of the third part of their Sins.</p>
               <p>Alſo in the Solemnity of the Converſion of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> there is an Indulgence therein of an hundred years, and of an hundred times forty days ſpace.</p>
               <p>Alſo in the Feaſt of the Holy Innocents, many of whoſe Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are buried in this Church, there was formerly an Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to be had of forty eight years, and of as many times forty days ſpace, but now there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
               <p>Alſo in the Dedication of the ſaid Church, which is the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctave of St. <hi>Martin,</hi> they gain an Indulgence of a thouſand years, and a thouſand times forty days ſpace, and moreover the forgiveneſs of the third part of their Sins.</p>
               <p>Alſo if any one enter into this Church of St. <hi>Paul</hi> upon a <hi>Sunday,</hi> he gains thereby as many Indulgences, as if he went to the Holy Sepulchre in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and to St. <hi>James</hi> in <hi>Galatia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo at this Church, amongſt the many other Altars, there are ſeven particular ones, as there are at St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s, at every of which there are twenty eight thouſand years Indulgences.</p>
               <p>Moreover in this Church of St. <hi>Paul</hi> are many Holy Reliques, as an Arm of St. <hi>Anne,</hi> the Mother of the Bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> the Chain wherewith St. <hi>Paul</hi> was bound, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all which are moſt carefully preſerved, and had in very great veneration;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152745:9"/>and as often as they ſhew the ſame, to thoſe that live in <hi>Rome,</hi> there is an Indulgence of three thouſand, to thoſe that live near <hi>Rome</hi> of ſix thouſand, and to thoſe that come from any far Country of twelve thouſand years; and moreover to each, of as many times forty days ſpace; and likewiſe to all the forgiveneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the third part of their Sins.</p>
               <p>In this Church alſo is an Image of the Crucifix that ſpake to St. <hi>Bridget,</hi> and there is alſo a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
               <p>The fourth of the ſeven Churches is the Church of St. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> in which they have any day ſix thouſand forty eight years, and ſix thouſand forty eight times forty days ſpace alſo of Indulgence, and moreover the Remiſſion of the third part of their Sins.</p>
               <p>Alſo in the Solemnities of the Conception, Nativity, Annunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, Purification, and Aſſumption of our Lady, they have each day therein ten thouſand years Indulgence, and full Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all their Sins.</p>
               <p>Alſo in this Church there are very many Altars, and at every Altar there are eighteen thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
               <p>Near the High Altar alſo is an Image of the Bleſſed Virgin, painted by St <hi>Luke,</hi> and there are infinite Indulgences.</p>
               <p>Alſo in this Church there is a Vault under ground, in which is kept the Crib or Manger wherein our Saviour was laid at his Birth, and there they gain an Indulgence of twelve thouſand years, and of twelve thouſand times forty days ſpace, and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over a forgiveneſs of the third part of their Sins.</p>
               <p>In this Church alſo is the Sepulchre of St. <hi>Girolame,</hi> and there they have twelve years Indulgence, and full Remiſſion of all their Sins.</p>
               <p>The fifth of the ſeven Churches of <hi>Rome</hi> is the Church of St. <hi>Laurence,</hi> in the which they have any day an Indulgence of ſix thouſand forty eight years, and of ſix thouſand forty eight times forty days ſpace; and moreover the forgiveneſs of the third part of their Sins.</p>
               <p>Alſo in this Church is the ſacred Body of St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> and one of the Stones with the which he was ſtoned, and there they have eight thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
               <p>In the ſame alſo is the moſt holy Body of the ſaid St. <hi>Laurence,</hi> and there they have a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152745:9"/>
               <p>Here alſo is the Stone whereon that Bleſſed Virgin, being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off the Grid-Iron, yielded up the Ghoſt, and there they have full Remiſſion of all their Sins.</p>
               <p>The ſixth of the ſeven Churches of <hi>Rome</hi> is the Church of St. <hi>Fabian</hi> and <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> in the which they have any day an Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of ſix thouſand forty eight years, and of as many Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantenes, one of which is forty days ſpace; and alſo the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of the third part of their ſins.</p>
               <p>Alſo there is there in any day a thouſand years Indulgence, granted by Pope <hi>Pelagio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this Church alſo, near to the High Altar, is the place where at firſt repoſed the Holy Bodies of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and there they have as many Indulgences as they can have at the Churches both of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſame alſo, who-ever cauſeth a Maſs to be ſaid at the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of St. <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> delivereth a Soul from Purgatory.</p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>Silveſter, Gregory, Honorio, Pelagio, Nicholas,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> Popes, granted to every one that ſhould (at what time of the year ſoever) viſit this Church, a thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
               <p>Underneath this Church, within the Earth, is the Cemitery of Pope <hi>Caliſto,</hi> into the which whoſoever enters confeſs'd and contrite, by the Merits of the ſame Saint, and of an hundred ſeventy four thouſand Martyrs, and of forty ſix other Holy Popes, who were there buried of which eighteen were Martyrs, gained a Plenary Remiſſion of all their ſins.</p>
               <p>There is another Cemitery in <hi>Rome,</hi> called the Cemitery of St. <hi>Calepodio,</hi> Martyr, in which whoſoever is buried hath a plenary Remiſſion of all his Sins.</p>
               <p>The ſeventh of the ſeven Churches of <hi>Rome</hi> is called <hi>Santa Croce,</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in the which there are any day ſix thouſand for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty eight years, and ſix forty eight times forty days ſpace of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, and moreover (to thoſe that obtain them) the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of the third part of their ſins.</p>
               <p>Alſo in the Dedication of this Church, made by St. <hi>Silveſter,</hi> which is celebrated the Vigil of St. <hi>Benedict Abbot</hi> in the Month of <hi>March,</hi> there is a plenary Remiſſion of all their ſins.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe in the Invention of the Title of Holy Croſs, which was there found in a Wall in the time of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Sixth, the twenty ſixth day of <hi>January,</hi> and more over any day in the Chappel of St. <hi>Elin,</hi> (wherein Women are not permitted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152745:10"/>to enter, unleſs once in the year) there is a Plenary Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
               <p>Alſo in this Church, every <hi>Sunday</hi> in the year, they have three hundred years, and three hundred times forty days ſpace of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, and likewiſe the forgiveneſs of the third part of their ſins, and moreover every <hi>Fryday</hi> in the year there are very many Indulgences.</p>
               <p>More-over in the ſame, any day throughout the year, they have a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
               <p>Note alſo that in theſe the aforeſaid ſeven Churches of <hi>Rome,</hi> which are the ſeven Lamps of the Holy <hi>Roman</hi> Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the aboveſaid Indulgences, there are others in great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, both plenary and not plenary, which they which come thereunto from any place to gain, do obtain any Day, any Hour, and any Minute; all which are alſo communicated to the Brothers and Siſters of the Society of the Habit of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</p>
               <p>And becauſe that in this Holy City of <hi>Rome</hi> are found many other Churches, where there are alſo granted moſt great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, appertaining as well alſo to thoſe inveſted with the Habit of the Servants of S. <hi>Mary,</hi> as to any others, it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite in the next place I ſhould put down them, which are as follow.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The Particular Indulgences at many Churches of <hi>Rome,</hi> beſides the Seven before mentioned, granted by divers Popes, and are daily to be gained, not only by Holy Pilgrims, and others, devoutly viſiting the ſame Churches, but alſo by the Brothers and Siſters of the Society of the Habit of the Servants of our Lady.</head>
                  <p>IN the Church of the Holy Ghoſt, any day, there are Six thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the <hi>Church</hi> of S. <hi>Anaſtatio,</hi> any day, ſix thouſand years.</p>
                  <p>At S. <hi>Vito</hi> and <hi>Marcello,</hi> any day, ſix thouſand years.</p>
                  <p>At S. <hi>Anges,</hi> any day, ſix thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>At S. <hi>Praſſede</hi> they have any day twelve thouſand years, and twelve thouſand times forty days ſpace, and the forgiveneſs of the third part of their ſins.</p>
                  <p>At S. <hi>Maria Scala Coeli,</hi> where are buried ten thouſand Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, there are any day 10000 years Indulgence.</p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:152745:10"/>
                  <p>At St. <hi>Bibiana,</hi> where are buried nine thouſand Martyrs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Women and Children, any day there are ninety thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>At St. <hi>Aleſſio,</hi> any day there are an hundred years, and one hundred times forty days ſpace.</p>
                  <p>At St. <hi>Balbina,</hi> any day there are ſeven years Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>At St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> any day forty years, and forty times forty days ſpace, and likewiſe the forgiveneſs of the third part of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ones ſins.</p>
                  <p>At St. <hi>Matthew Apoſtle,</hi> in <hi>Merula,</hi> any day a thouſand years, and a thouſand times forty days ſpace, and the forgiveneſs of the ſeventh part of every ones ſins.</p>
                  <p>At the Chappel <hi>del Salvatore in San Luigi nel Rion di St. Suſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chio,</hi> any day they have a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                  <p>At St. <hi>Lucia della Chiavica del Rione di Ponte,</hi> there is any day a plenary Indulgence granted by very many Popes.</p>
                  <p>At St. <hi>Coſmo</hi> and <hi>Damiano,</hi> any day as many times as they enter into the Church, they have ſo many years Indulgence granted by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Firſt.</p>
                  <p>At St. <hi>Girolamo,</hi> near the Palace of <hi>Monſignor Illuſtriſſimo Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſe,</hi> any day there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>At St. <hi>Mario del Pianto,</hi> any day is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>At St. <hi>Catherine de Fornari,</hi> the Monaſtery <hi>delle Citelle,</hi> any day there is a Pardon.</p>
                  <p>At St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s, in <hi>Carcere Pulliano,</hi> any day they have a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand two hundred Indulgences, and the Remiſſion of the third part of their ſins, and in Feſtival days they have twice as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
                  <p>At St. <hi>Clement,</hi> any day they have forty years, and forty times forty days ſpace of Indulgence, granted by Pope <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſio,</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third, and the forgiveneſs of the third part of their ſins, and in <hi>Lent</hi> they are all doubled.</p>
                  <p>At St. <hi>Rocco a Ripetta,</hi> any day there is a Plenary Indulgence granted by Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth, and many other Popes.</p>
                  <p>At the place where St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid <hi>Domine, quo vadis,</hi> any day there are many Indulgences.</p>
                  <p>At St. <hi>Euſebio,</hi> any day there are ſeven thouſand eight hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years, and ſeven thouſand eight hundred times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:152745:11"/>
                  <p>At St. <hi>Pudentiana</hi> there are more than three thouſand Bodies of Holy Martyrs, buryed in the Cemitery of St. <hi>Priſcilla;</hi> and there for each body, any day, is one year, and once forty days ſpace of Indulgence, and the Remiſſion of the third part of every ones ſins, granted by bleſſed <hi>Simpliciano</hi> Pope.</p>
                  <p>At <hi>Madonna della Trinita</hi> in S. <hi>Salvatore,</hi> there is any day a great pardon.</p>
                  <p>At <hi>Madonna di Monferrato,</hi> near <hi>Corte Savella,</hi> there are any day infinite Indulgences.</p>
                  <p>At S. <hi>Maria libera nos à poenis Inferni,</hi> S. <hi>Silveſter</hi> the Pope granted any day eight years Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>At the Chappel of S. <hi>Mary Imperatrice</hi> towards S. <hi>John La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran,</hi> there is the Image of S. <hi>Mary</hi> the Virgin, which ſpake to S. <hi>Gregory,</hi> and he granted to each one that ſhould ſay there three <hi>Pater-noſter's</hi> and three <hi>Ave-Maria's,</hi> for every time they ſhould ſay the ſame, ſeventeen years Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>At S. <hi>Maria del' Horto,</hi> near <hi>Ripa,</hi> is an Hoſpital for the ſick, and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>At S. <hi>Maria de miracoli à canto le mura della Porta del Popolo,</hi> there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>At S. <hi>James</hi> in <hi>Auguſta</hi> every <hi>Saturday</hi> in the year they have the forgiveneſs of the third part of their ſins; and upon the day of the Annunciation, and the firſt day of <hi>May,</hi> and the Anniverſary of any one dead, they have a plenary Remiſſion, and many other Priviledges.</p>
                  <p>At S. <hi>John Aino,</hi> near <hi>Corte Savella,</hi> every ſecond <hi>Sonday</hi> in each Month, and many other dayes in the year, is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>M. S. <hi>Maria Liberatione</hi> which is in <hi>Fore Romano</hi> there are any day eleven-thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the Church of the Order of the <hi>Minims,</hi> alias S. <hi>Franceſco di Paula,</hi> called the <hi>Trinity,</hi> from the twenty ſecond day of <hi>Lent,</hi> until after the <hi>Octave</hi> of the Reſurrection, whoſoever ſays three <hi>Pater-noſter's</hi> and three <hi>Ave-Maria's</hi> to the honour of the holy Trinity, doth obtain any day a thouſand years In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, granted by Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth.</p>
                  <p>And any <hi>Sunday</hi> of <hi>Lent,</hi> viſiting the ſaid Church, and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing three <hi>Pater-noſter's</hi> and three <hi>Ave-Maria's,</hi> they gain a ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152745:11"/>Indulgence, granted by <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth: And from <hi>Eaſter-Eve</hi> at night, until Sun-riſing the next Morning, ſaying there <hi>Pater-noſter's,</hi> and three <hi>Ave-Maria's,</hi> to the honour of the holy Trinity, they obtain a plenary Indulgence granted by the ſame Pope <hi>Leo:</hi> And from <hi>Whitſon</hi> Eve at night until <hi>Whitſunday</hi> at night, and from the Evening before <hi>Trinity-Sunday,</hi> until <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity-Sunday</hi> at night, ſaying three <hi>Pater-noſter's</hi> and three <hi>Ave-Maria's</hi> in honour as aforeſaid, they gain a plenary Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                  <p>Moreover in the ſaid Church, any ſecond <hi>Sunday</hi> of the Month, every month throughout the whole year, there is a ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Indulgence granted by Pope <hi>Siſto</hi> the Fourth.</p>
                  <p>In S. <hi>Maria de gli Angioli,</hi> there are granted by Pope <hi>Pio</hi> the Fourth, the ſame Priviledges, the ſame Stations, and the ſame Indulgences, which are to be had at <hi>Santa Croce</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> and moreover there is given to all that ſhall viſit the ſaid Church, in the days of the Nativity and Reſurrection of our Lord, and the day of <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> and the days of the Nativity, Purification and Aſſumption of our Lady, and in the day of the Dedication of the ſame Church, a plenary Indulgence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>Here followeth a Summary of the Indulgences and Stations in the Churches within and without <hi>Rome,</hi> beſides the Indulgences of the Seven Churches, and of the other before mentioned; the which In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences and Stations are appointed from day to day, from month to month, and from time to time, according to the Circle of the year: And the Indulgences are communicated, not only to devout Pilgrims, and others viſiting the Churches where the ſame are to be obtained, but alſo to the Society of the Habit of the Servants of <hi>S. Mary.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="subpart__month">
                     <head>JAN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ARY.</head>
                     <p>THE firſt day, to wit, the Solemnity of the Circumciſion of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, is a Station to the Church of St. <hi>Maria</hi> in <hi>Traſtevere ad Fontes Olei,</hi> and there they have twenty five thouſand years Indulgences, and a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins, granted by Pope <hi>Celeſtine</hi> the Second.</p>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:152745:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <p>The ſame day there is a plenary Indulgence at theſe four Churches: to wit,
<list>
                           <item>The Church of S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The Church of S. <hi>Maria</hi> in <hi>Araceli,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The Church of S. <hi>Mark,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>And the Church of Saint <hi>John Lateran.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>The day of the <hi>Epiphany</hi> of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, which is the ſixth day, there is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and there they have twenty eight thouſand years, and twenty eight thouſand times forty days ſpace of Indulgences, and the forgiveneſs of the third part of their ſins: And thus it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth during the <hi>Octave.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Spirito</hi> in <hi>Saſſia,</hi> are the ſame day ten thouſand years Indulgence: and thus it continues alſo during the <hi>Octave,</hi> granted by Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the Seventh.</p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> the ſame day, there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Giuliano</hi> Martyr, which is the ſeventh day, at his Church there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the <hi>Octave</hi> of the <hi>Epiphany,</hi> which is the thirteenth day, is a Station to S. <hi>Peter</hi>'s, and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Alſo the ſame day is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Mark,</hi> and there is a plenary Indulgence, granted by Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Faelix</hi> Martyr, which is the fourteenth day, is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Sebaſtian;</hi> and there are ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Paul</hi> the firſt Eremite, which is the fifteenth day, is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Trinity,</hi> and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the Feaſt of the five Holy Martyrs of the Order of the <hi>Minors,</hi> and of S. <hi>Macello</hi> Pope and Martyr, which is the ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day, there is at the Church of S. <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> ten thouſand years Indulgence; and moreover every one hath the remiſſion of all his ſins.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Anthony</hi> Abbot, which is the ſeventeenth day, there is at his Church a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>At S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> the ſame day, they have remiſſion of all their ſins.</p>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:152745:12"/>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair, inſtituted by Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Fourth, in the year 1557. which is the eighteenth day, is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and there is a plenary Indulgence, and they ſhew the Chair, and the Holy Vault.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day, it being the day alſo of S. <hi>Priſca,</hi> is a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to her Church, and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond <hi>Sunday</hi> after <hi>Epiphany</hi> is a Station to <hi>San Spirito</hi> in <hi>Saſſia,</hi> and there they have three thouſand years Indulgence, and three thouſand times forty days ſpace, and the forgiveneſs of the third part of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Fabian</hi> and S. <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> which is the twentieth day, is a Station to their Church, and there is a plenary Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Agnes</hi> Virgin, which is the twenty-firſt day, is a Station to her Church, and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>At S. <hi>Maria Maggiore</hi> they have remiſſion of all their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Vincenzo</hi> and S. <hi>Anaſtaſio,</hi> which is the twenty ſecond day, is a Station to their Church, and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the Converſion of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> which is the twenty-fifth is a Station to his Church, and there they have an hundred years, and an hundred times forty days ſpace of Indulgence; and moreover a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>John Chriſoſtom,</hi> which is the twenty ſixth day, is a Station to his Church, and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Moreover the ſame day in the Church of S. <hi>Maria ſcala Coeli</hi> is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the ſecond Feaſt of S. <hi>Agnes,</hi> which is the twenty eighth day, at the Church of S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> is a plenary In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Ciro</hi> and S. <hi>John,</hi> which is the one and thirtieth day, at their Church there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Moreover the ſame day is a Station to the Church of <hi>Santa Croce</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The laſt <hi>Sunday</hi> of the Month of <hi>January</hi> is a Station alſo to the ſame Church in memory of the invention of the Title of the Holy Croſs, and there is a plenary Indulgence granted by Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the Sixth.</p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Maria de gli Angioli,</hi> the ſame day, is the like Indulgence.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart__month">
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:152745:13"/>
                     <head>FEBR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ARY.</head>
                     <p>THE day of S. <hi>Bridgit,</hi> which is the firſt day, there is a Station to her Church, where is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Alſo, the ſame day there is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> in which is the Body of S. <hi>Ignatio,</hi> and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the purification of the glorious Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which is the ſecond day, is a Station to S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> and and there they have a Thouſand years Indulgence, and a plenary Remiſſion of all their Sins.</p>
                     <p>Moreover the ſame day, is an Indulgence in theſe four Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, to wit,
<list>
                           <item>At S. <hi>Maria de li Angioli</hi> granted by Pope <hi>Pio</hi> the third.</item>
                           <item>At S. <hi>Maria in via Lata,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>At S. <hi>Maria della Pace,</hi> and,</item>
                           <item>At S. <hi>Maria del Popolo</hi> is a plenary Indulgence granted by Pope <hi>Siſto</hi> the fourth; and thus there is daily during the Octave of the Feaſt.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Blaſe,</hi> which is the third day, at his Church there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Agatha,</hi> which is the fift-day, at her Church there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Alſo the ſame day at <hi>Santa</hi> Croce is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Apollonia,</hi> which is the ninth day, at the Church of S. <hi>Luigi,</hi> is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair at <hi>Antioch,</hi> which is the twenty-ſecond day, in the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> there is a plenary Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, alſo an Indulgence of a thouſand years, and moreover an Indulgence of five hundred fifty eight thouſand nine hundred ſixty eight years, and two hundred eighty five days.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Mathias</hi> Apoſtle, which is the twenty-fourth day, there is at his Church a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Moreover in the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and in the Church of S. <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Philip,</hi> in all the feaſts of the Apoſtles, there are full remiſſion of every ones Sins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day is a Station to S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> where is the Body of S. <hi>Mathias,</hi> and there is a plenary Indulgence: And
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152745:13"/>moreover an Indulgence of one hundred fifty ſix thouſand two hundred and ſixty years, and two hundred ſixty five days.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Coſtanza,</hi> which the twenty-ſixth day, is a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Church of S. <hi>Agnes,</hi> and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart__month">
                     <head>MARCH.</head>
                     <p>EVERY <hi>Fryday</hi> in the Month of <hi>March,</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Aquine,</hi> which is the ſeventh day, at his Church, there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Alſo the ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>Maria Sophra la Miner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va,</hi> is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Gregory</hi> Pope, which is the twelfth day, is a Station to his Church, and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day alſo, in S. <hi>Peters</hi> Church, there is a plenary In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Joſeph,</hi> which is the nineteenth day, at the Church of S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> is a plenary of Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the Vigil of S. <hi>Benedict,</hi> which is the twentieth day is a Station to the Chappel of S. <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Alſo the ſame day there is a Station to the Church of <hi>Santa Croce</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Moreover the ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>Maria de gli An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gioli</hi> is the like Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Benedict</hi> Abbot, which is the twenty-firſt day, at the Church of S. <hi>Peter</hi> there are an hundred years of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and moreover an Indulgence of one hundred fifty nine thouſand one hundred ſixty four years, and fourty days.</p>
                     <p>The Annunciation of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which is the twenty-fifth day, at her Church there are Infinite Indulgences; and moreover Stations with plenary Indulgences during the whole Octave of the feaſt.</p>
                     <p>Alſo the ſame day there is a plenary Indulgence at theſe Churches following; to wit,
<list>
                           <item>S. <hi>Maria della pace,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>S. <hi>Maria del popolo.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>And S. <hi>Giacomo</hi> in <hi>Auguſta.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Alſo the ſaid day of the Annunciation in the Church of S. <hi>Peter</hi> are a thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart__month">
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:152745:14"/>
                     <head>The Indulgences which are dayly in Lent, and Eaſter-Week.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. THE firſt day of <hi>Lent</hi> is a Station to <hi>Santa Sabina,</hi> and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The ſecond day is a Station to the Church of <hi>S. Gregorio,</hi> and there are a thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The third day, is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. The fourth day is a Station to S. <hi>Triſone,</hi> and there are eight thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. The fifth day, which is the firſt <hi>Sunday</hi> in <hi>Lent,</hi> is a Stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> and there they have eighteen thouſand years Indulgence, and full remiſſion of all their ſins.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Upon <hi>Monday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Peter</hi> in <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula,</hi> and there they have a thouſand years Indulgence, and moreover a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. Upon <hi>Tueſday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Anaſtaſia,</hi> and there is an Indulgence <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> years, and of as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times forty days ſpace, and the deliverance of a ſoul from Purgatory.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Upon <hi>Wedneſday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> and there they have an Indulgence of twenty-eight thouſand years, and of twenty-eight thouſand times forty days ſpace, and the remiſſion of the third part of their ſins.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. Upon <hi>Thurſday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Lawrence</hi> in <hi>Paliſperna,</hi> which is the place where S. <hi>Laurence</hi> was broiled, and there they have ten years Indulgence, and plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. Upon <hi>Fryday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Apoſtolo,</hi> where inhabit the <hi>Fryers Minors,</hi> and there they have twelve thouſand years Indulgence, and the forgiveneſs of all their ſins.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. Upon <hi>Saturday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and there they have an Indulgence of eighteen thouſand years, and of eighteen thouſand times forty days ſpace, and moreover a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>Maria del Popolo,</hi> and at
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152745:14"/>the Church of S. <hi>Maria della Pace,</hi> there is a Plenary Indulgence, and the ſame there is every <hi>Saturday</hi> in <hi>Lent.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="12">12. The ſecond <hi>Sunday</hi> in <hi>Lent,</hi> is a <hi>Station</hi> to the Church of S. <hi>Maria della Navicella,</hi> and there they have eighteen thouſand years, and eighteen thouſand times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. Upon <hi>Monday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Clement,</hi> and there they have eleven thouſand years Indulgence, and the forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the third part of their ſins.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. Upon <hi>Tueſday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Balbina,</hi> and there are ten thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. Upon <hi>Wedneſday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Cecilia,</hi> and there are ten thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. Upon <hi>Thurſday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Maria</hi> in <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtevere,</hi> and there are ten thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="17">17. Upon <hi>Friday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Vitale,</hi> and there are ten thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. Upon <hi>Saturday</hi> is a Station to the Church of <hi>San Pietro,</hi> and <hi>Marcellino,</hi> and there each hath ten thouſand years Indulgence, and the full remiſſion of his ſins; and moreover, the delivering of a Soul from Purgatory.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. The third <hi>Sunday</hi> in <hi>Lent</hi> is a Station to <hi>San Lorenzo, fuori della Mura,</hi> and there is an Indulgence of nineteen thouſand years, and of forty eight times forty days ſpace, and the deliverance of a Soul from Purgatory.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. Upon <hi>Monday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Mark,</hi> and there are ten thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="21">21. Upon <hi>Tueſday</hi> there is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiana,</hi> and there are ten thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="22">22. Upon <hi>Wedneſday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Siſto,</hi> and there are ten thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. Upon <hi>Thurſday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Coſmo</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miano,</hi> and there are ten thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at night, at the Church of S. <hi>Maria del Popolo,</hi> and S. <hi>Maria della Pace,</hi> there is a Plenary Indulgence; and the like is there every day to be had, until after the <hi>Octave</hi> of <hi>Eaſter.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Maria del Pianto,</hi> upon the ſame day alſo is a Plenary Indulgence, granted by Pope <hi>Julio</hi> the ſecond.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, at the ſaid Churches of <hi>San Maria del Popolo,</hi> and <hi>della Pace,</hi> Pope <hi>Siſto</hi> the fourth granted, from the midſt of <hi>Lent,</hi> until after the <hi>Octave</hi> of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> any day, a thouſand years, and a thouſand times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:152745:15"/>
                     <p n="24">24. Upon <hi>Friday</hi> is a Station to S. <hi>Laurence</hi> in <hi>Lucina,</hi> and there are ten thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="25">25. Upon <hi>Saturday</hi> is a Station to S. <hi>Laurence</hi> in <hi>Santa Suſana,</hi> and there are ten thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at the Churches both of S. <hi>Maria del Popolo,</hi> and S. <hi>Maria della Pace,</hi> is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="26">26. The fourth <hi>Sunday</hi> in <hi>Lent</hi> is a Station to the Church of <hi>Santa Croce</hi> in <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and there is a Plenary Indulgence; and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, they deliver a Soul from the Pains of Purgatory.</p>
                     <p>Alſo the ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>Maria de gli Angioli,</hi> they have a Plenary Indulgence, and likewiſe they deliver a Soul from Purgatory.</p>
                     <p n="27">27. Upon <hi>Monday</hi> is a Station to the Church of the <hi>Quatri Santi Coronati,</hi> and there are ten thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="28">28. Upon <hi>Tueſday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Laurence</hi> in <hi>Damaſo,</hi> and there are ten thouſand years Indulgence; and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, the remiſſion of the third part of every ones ſins.</p>
                     <p n="29">29. Upon <hi>Wedneſday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and there they have ten thouſand years Indulgence, and the forgiveneſs of the third part of their ſins.</p>
                     <p n="30">30. Upon <hi>Thurſday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Sylveſter,</hi> and there are ten thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Alſo the ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>Martin</hi> in <hi>Monte,</hi> there are ten thouſand years Indulgence, granted by Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fourth.</p>
                     <p n="31">31. Upon <hi>Friday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Euſebio,</hi> and there are ten thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="32">32. Upon <hi>Saturday</hi> is a Station to S. <hi>Nicholas</hi> in <hi>Carcere,</hi> and there they have ten thouſand years Indulgence, and a Plenary remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day both at the Church of S. <hi>Maria del Popolo,</hi> and at the Church of S. <hi>Maria della Pace,</hi> there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="33">33. The fifth <hi>Sunday</hi> in <hi>Lent,</hi> called <hi>Paſſion Sunday,</hi> is a Station to S. <hi>Peter</hi>'s, and there they have an Indulgence of twenty eight thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years, and of as many times forty days ſpace, and the forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the third part of their ſins.</p>
                     <p n="34">34. Upon <hi>Monday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Griſogon,</hi> and there are ten thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="35">35. Upon <hi>Tueſday</hi> there is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Ciriaco,</hi> and there are ten thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="36">36. Upon <hi>Wedneſday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Marcello,</hi> where are the Brothers of the Servants, and there are ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:152745:15"/>
                     <p n="37">37. Upon <hi>Thurſday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Apollinare,</hi> and there are ten thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="38">38. Upon <hi>Friday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Stephen</hi> in <hi>Monte Celio,</hi> and there is the deliverance of a Soul from the Pains of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory.</p>
                     <p n="39">39. Upon <hi>Saturday</hi> is a Station to S. <hi>John ante Portam Latinam,</hi> and there are thirteen thouſand years Indulgence, and the delivering of a Soul from Purgatory.</p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Maria del Popolo,</hi> and at the Church of S. <hi>Maria della Pace,</hi> there is the ſame day a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="40">40. The ſixth <hi>Sunday</hi> in <hi>Lent,</hi> called <hi>Palm-Sunday,</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> and there they have twenty five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years, and twenty five thouſand times forty days ſpace of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence; and moreover, a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>Bartholemew nell' Iſola,</hi> there are two hundred years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Alſo the ſame day at night, at the Church of our Lady <hi>de Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celi,</hi> every day until after the <hi>Octave</hi> of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="41">41. Upon <hi>Holy Monday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Paraſſede,</hi> and there they have fifteen thouſand years Indulgence, and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of the third part of their ſins, and moreover a Plenary In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Mark,</hi> from <hi>Holy Monday</hi> until after <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Tueſday,</hi> any day there is a Plenary Indulgence, granted by Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the ſecond.</p>
                     <p n="42">42. Upon <hi>Holy Tueſday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Priſca,</hi> and there they have eighteen thouſand years Indulgence, and a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p n="43">43. Upon <hi>Holy Wedneſday</hi> is a Station to S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> and there they have twenty thouſand years Indulgence, and likewiſe a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day is the morning, after they have ſang <hi>High-Maſs</hi> in the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> they ſhew the <hi>Holy Vault.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="44">44. Upon <hi>Holy Thurſday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>John La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran,</hi> and there they have eleven thouſand years, and eleven thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times forty days ſpace of Indulgence; and moreover, twice a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day the Pope waſheth the Feet of twelve poor People, and there is read the <hi>Bull</hi> concerning the Supper of our Lord.</p>
                     <p n="45">45. Upon <hi>Holy Friday</hi> is a Station to the Church of <hi>Santa Croce</hi>
                        <pb n="20" facs="tcp:152745:16"/>in <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and there they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Maria de gli Angioli,</hi> the ſame day there is the like Indulgence.</p>
                     <p n="46">46. Upon <hi>Holy Saturday</hi> is a Station to S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> and there they have twelve thouſand years Indulgence, and forty eight <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantines,</hi> each of which is forty days ſpace; and moreover, they have a plenary remiſſion of all their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at S. <hi>Maria del Popolo,</hi> and at S. <hi>Maria della Pace,</hi> they have plenary remiſſion of all their ſins.</p>
                     <p>Upon <hi>Eaſter-Day</hi> is a Station to S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> and there they have an Indulgence of twenty eight thouſand years, and of twenty eight thouſand times forty days ſpace; and moreover, a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Maria de gli Angioli,</hi> the ſame day there is the like Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, the ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>Spirito</hi> in <hi>Saſſia,</hi> there are two thouſand years Indulgence: And thus there are daily, until after the <hi>Octave</hi> of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> granted by Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the eighth.</p>
                     <p>Upon <hi>Eaſter Monday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and there they have twenty eight thouſand years Indulgence, and a ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>Upon <hi>Eaſter Tueſday</hi> there is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and there they have an Indulgence of twenty thouſand years, and of twenty eight thouſand times forty days ſpace, and a plenary remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>Upon <hi>Eaſter Wedneſday</hi> there is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence fuori le Mura,</hi> and there is an Indulgence of eighteen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years, and of as many times forty days ſpace, and the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of a Soul from Purgatory.</p>
                     <p>Upon <hi>Thurſday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Apoſtolo,</hi> and there they have fifteen thouſand years Indulgence; and moreover, a ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>Upon <hi>Friday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Maria Rotonda,</hi> and there are fifteen thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Upon <hi>Saturday</hi> is a Station to S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> and there they have fifteen thouſand years Indulgence, and twice a plenary remiſſion of their ſins. And this is the day in which the Pope bleſſeth the <hi>Agnus Dei's</hi> made with white Wax.</p>
                     <p>Upon the <hi>Sunday</hi> of the <hi>Octave</hi> of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Pancratio,</hi> and there they have fifteen thouſand years
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152745:16"/>Indulgence; and moreover, twice a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, alſo the ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Friday</hi> after the <hi>Octave</hi> of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> at the Church of S. <hi>Maria Rotonda,</hi> there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Sunday</hi> following, to wit, the ſecond <hi>Sunday</hi> after <hi>Eaſter,</hi> at the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart__month">
                     <head>APRIL.</head>
                     <p>AT the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> any day they have twelve thouſand years Indulgence, and twelve thouſand times forty days ſpace, and the remiſſion of the third part of their ſins: And thus they have, until after the firſt of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>At the Church <hi>della Nonciata,</hi> any day there are a thouſand years Indulgence; and thus it continueth until after the firſt day of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The firſt day of <hi>April,</hi> which is the <hi>Octave</hi> of the <hi>Annunciation,</hi> at the ſame Church there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Maria del Popolo,</hi> the ſame day there is a Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Maria Egittiaca,</hi> which is the ſecond day, at her Church there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Pancratio</hi> Biſhop, which is the third day, they have at his Church a plenary remiſſion of all their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Vicenzo</hi> Confeſſor, who was of the Order of the <hi>Dominican Fryers,</hi> at his Church, there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>George,</hi> which is the twenty third day, is a Station to his Church, and there they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins, and alſo a thouſand years Indulgence: and moreover, an hundred fifty four thouſand nine hundred and thirteen years, and two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſixty days.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> there is a Plenary Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Mark</hi> Evangeliſt, is a Station to his Church, and there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, the ſame day, at the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> is a Plenary Indulgence; and alſo an Indulgence of an hundred fifty four thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand nine hundred and ninety years, and of two hundred and nine days: And moreover, when the Prieſts and Brothers go there the ſame day in Proceſſion, there are twenty eight thouſand years,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152745:17"/>and twenty eight thouſand times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Vitale,</hi> which is the twenty ninth day, is a Station to his Church, and there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Peter</hi> Martyr, which is the ſame day, at the Church of S. <hi>Maria della Minerva,</hi> is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, the ſame day is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Mark,</hi> and there they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart__month">
                     <head>MAY.</head>
                     <p>AT the Church <hi>Della Nonciata,</hi> any day, there are a thouſand years Indulgence, and it continueth thus until after the firſt of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> any day, they have an Indulgence of twelve thouſand years, and of twelve thouſand times forty days ſpace, and the remiſſion of the third part of their ſins: And thus they have, until after the firſt of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Every <hi>Sunday</hi> in the Month of <hi>May,</hi> at the Church of S. <hi>Sebaſtiano,</hi> is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>James,</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> Apoſtles, which is the firſt day of <hi>May,</hi> at their Church there is a plenary remiſſion of all ſin; and ſo there is in all the Feaſts of the Apoſtles.</p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Peter</hi> is the like Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, the ſame day is a Plenary Indulgence at theſe three Churches: to wit,
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Santo Apoſtolo.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Santa Maria Maggiore,</hi> and</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>San Giacomo</hi> in <hi>Auguſta.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>The day of the Invention of the <hi>Holy Croſs,</hi> which is the third day, there is a Station to <hi>Santa Croce</hi> in <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and there they have remiſſion of all their ſins, and moreover infinite Indulgences, and it continueth thus during the <hi>Octave</hi> of the ſame Feaſt.</p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Maria de gli Angioli</hi> is the like Indulgences; and at the Church of S. <hi>Maria Rotonda</hi> is a plenary remiſſion of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ones ſins, it being the day of the Conſecration of the ſame Church.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, the ſame day at the moſt Holy Crucifix, in the Church of S. <hi>Marcello,</hi> there is a Plenary Indulgence granted by Pope <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the thirteenth.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Monica,</hi> Mother of S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> which is the fourth day, at the Church of S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> there is a Plenary Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and moreover alſo infinite Indulgences.</p>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:152745:17"/>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>John ante Portam Latinam,</hi> which is the ſixth day, they have in his Church a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>At S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> the ſame day there is a Plenary Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and the deliverance of a Soul from Purgatory.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, the ſame day is a Station to S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> and there every one hath a plenary remiſſion of his ſins, and delivereth a Soul from Purgatory.</p>
                     <p>The day of the Apparition of S. <hi>Michael,</hi> at his Church they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at S. <hi>Maria Maggiore</hi> is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, from this day to the end of the <hi>Calends</hi> of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> at the Church of S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> any day, there are three times a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the <hi>Octave</hi> of the Feaſt of the <hi>Holy Croſs,</hi> which is the tenth day, at the Church of <hi>Santa Croce</hi> is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day, at the Church of S. <hi>Maria de li Angioli,</hi> there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Nereo</hi> and <hi>Archileo,</hi> which is the twelfth day, at their Church there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day alſo, at the Church of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Vittore</hi> and <hi>Corona,</hi> which is the fourteenth day, at their Church there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Potentiana,</hi> which is the nineteenth day, at her Church there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Bernardino,</hi> which is the twentieth day, is a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Church of S. <hi>Maria</hi> in <hi>Araceli,</hi> and there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Helena,</hi> which is the twenty firſt day, at her Church is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Petronilla</hi> Virgin, they have at S. <hi>Peter</hi>'s a thouſand years, and a thouſand times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>And note, that from the day of S. <hi>Bernardino</hi> aforeſaid, until af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the firſt day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> at the Church of S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> they have any day a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart__liturgical_season">
                     <head>The Indulgences in <hi>Aſcenſion</hi> and <hi>Whitſun</hi>-Week.</head>
                     <p>UPon <hi>Letany Monday,</hi> that is to ſay, the <hi>Monday</hi> before the Feaſt of the Aſcenſion of our Lord, they go in Proceſſion to the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and there they have twenty eight thouſand
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152745:18"/>years, and twenty eight thouſand times forty days ſpace of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                     <p>Upon <hi>Letany Tueſday,</hi> at the Church of S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> there is an Indulgence of twenty eight thouſand years, and of twenty eight thouſand times forty days ſpace.</p>
                     <p>Upon <hi>Letany Wedneſday,</hi> at S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> they have an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence of twenty eight thouſand years, and of twenty eight thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times forty days ſpace, and the remiſſion of all their ſins, grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Pope <hi>Pio</hi> the ſecond, becauſe that upon that day they cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the Tranſlation of S. <hi>Girolamo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Upon <hi>Thurſday,</hi> which is the day of the Aſcenſion of our Lord, at the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> there is an Indulgence of twenty eight thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years, and of twenty eight thouſand times forty days ſpace; and moreover, a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Alſo the ſame day, at the Church of <hi>San Spirito</hi> in <hi>Saſſia,</hi> there are twenty eight thouſand eight hundred years Indulgence, granted by <hi>Boniface</hi> the eighth.</p>
                     <p>Upon <hi>Whitſun-Eve</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> and there they have fifteen thouſand years Indulgence, and a plena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>Upon <hi>Whit-Sunday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and there is a plenary remiſſion of their ſins, and moreover infinite Indulgences.</p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Maria de gli Angioli,</hi> the ſame day, they have a plenary forgiveneſs of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, the ſame day, at the Church of <hi>San Spirito</hi> in <hi>Saſſia,</hi> they have an Indulgence of four thouſand years, and of eight hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times forty days ſpace, and the remiſſion of the ſeventh part of their ſins, granted by Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the fourth.</p>
                     <p>Upon <hi>Whitſun-Monday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Peter</hi> in <hi>Vincula,</hi> and there they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>Alſo the ſame day, at the Church of S. <hi>Maria de gli Angioli,</hi> is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Upon <hi>Whitſun-Tueſday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Anaſtaſia,</hi> and there is an Indulgence of eighteen thouſand years, and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Upon <hi>Ember-Wedneſday</hi> is a Station to S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> and there they have an Indulgence of twenty eight thouſand years, and of twenty eight thouſand times forty days ſpace, and the remiſſion of the third part of their ſins; and moreover, a Plenary Remiſſion.</p>
                     <p>Upon <hi>Thurſday</hi> is a Station to S. <hi>Laurence Juorile Mura,</hi> and there they have an Indulgence of eighteen thouſand years, and of eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152745:18"/>thouſand times forty days ſpace, and the remiſſion of the third part of their ſins; and moreover, a plenary remiſſion, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering of a Soul from Purgatory.</p>
                     <p>Upon <hi>Ember-Friday</hi> is a Station to S. <hi>Apoſtolo,</hi> and there they have eighteen thouſand years Indulgence, and a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>Upon <hi>Ember-Saturday</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and there they have an Indulgence of eighteen thouſand years, and of eighteen thouſand times forty days ſpace, and the forgiveneſs of the third part of their ſins; and moreover, a plenary remiſſion, and the deliverance of a Soul from Purgatory.</p>
                     <p>Alſo the ſame day, at the Church of S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Upon <hi>Corpus Chriſti</hi>-day is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and there they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins, and it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth during the <hi>Octave</hi> of the Feaſt: And moreover, they have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Indulgences granted by Pope <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the fourth to them, that then, and during the <hi>Octave,</hi> ſhall be found preſent at Divine Offices.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, the ſame day is a Station to <hi>San Spirito</hi> in <hi>Saſſia,</hi> and there they have a thouſand years Indulgence, and the remiſſion of the ſeventh part of their ſins, and it continueth during the <hi>Octave.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The day of the <hi>Octave</hi> of <hi>Corpus Chriſti</hi> is a Station to S. <hi>Mark,</hi> and there is a Plenary Indulgence granted by Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Second.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart__month">
                     <head>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NE.</head>
                     <p>AT the Church <hi>della Nonciata,</hi> any day, there are a thouſand years Indulgence; and thus it continueth until after the firſt of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> they have any day twelve thouſand years, and twelve thouſand times forty days ſpace of Indulgence, and the remiſſion of third part of their ſins: And thus it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth alſo, until after the firſt day of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> any day, they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins: And thus it likewiſe continueth until after the firſt of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Marcellin, Peter,</hi> and <hi>Eraſmo,</hi> which is the ſecond day, is a Station to S. <hi>Marcellino,</hi> and there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> there are a thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond <hi>Sunday</hi> of <hi>June</hi> is a Statio ut S. <hi>Maria della Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione,</hi>
                        <pb n="26" facs="tcp:152745:19"/>and there they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins, granted by Pope <hi>Siſto</hi> the fourth.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Barnabas,</hi> which is the eleventh day, is a Station to his Church, and there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at S. <hi>Peter</hi>'s there are ſix hundred years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Anthony,</hi> Confeſſor of the Order of S. <hi>Francis,</hi> which is the thirteenth day, is a Station to S. <hi>Maria</hi> in <hi>Araceli,</hi> and there they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins, granted by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Vito, Modeſto,</hi> and <hi>Creſcentio,</hi> which is the fifteenth day, is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Vito</hi> in <hi>Macello,</hi> and there they have ſix thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> they have an hundred years, and an hundred times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Paulino,</hi> Biſhop and Confeſſor, which is the twenty ſecond day, at the Church of S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> there are ſeven thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the Nativity of S. <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> which is the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty fourth day, at the Church of S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> they have a plena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry remiſſion of their ſins and an Indulgence of one hundred fifty four thouſand nine hundred eighty five years, and forty five days, and the delivering of a Soul from Purgatory, granted by <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth: But the ſame Pope hath willed, that whoſoever gaineth this Indulgence, ſhall ſay a <hi>Corona</hi> for his Holineſs.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>John de Fiorentini,</hi> is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> which is the twenty ſixth day, at the Church of S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> are a thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Leo</hi> Pope, which is the twenty eighth day, at S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> they have a thouſand years, and a thouſand times forty days ſpace of Indulgence: And moreover, it being the <hi>Vigil</hi> of S. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> Apoſtles, which is the twenty ninth day, is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and there is a Plenary In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence; and ſo likewiſe there is in all the Feaſts of the Apoſtles.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, at the Church of the ſaid two Apoſtles the ſame day, beſides a Plenary Indulgence, there are one hundred fifty nine thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand nine hundred ſixty three years, and forty five days of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>James,</hi> the ſame day, there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:152745:19"/>
                     <p>The day of the Commemoration of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> which is the thirtieth day, is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and there they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins; and moreover, infinite Indulgences.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart__month">
                     <head>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LY.</head>
                     <p>AT the Church <hi>della Nonciata,</hi> any day, there are a thouſand years Indulgence; and thus it continueth until after the firſt of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>At S. <hi>Peters,</hi> any day, there are twelve thouſand years Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and twelve thouſand times forty days ſpace, and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of the third part of their ſins: And thus alſo it continueth until after the firſt day of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>At S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> any day, they have a Plenary remiſſion of their ſins; and it continueth, as aforeſaid.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Octave</hi> of S. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> which is the firſt day of <hi>July,</hi> at the Church of S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the Viſitation of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which is the ſecond day, is a Station to S. <hi>Maria del Popolo,</hi> and there they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins, granted by Pope <hi>Siſto</hi> the fourth; and it continueth thus the whole <hi>Octave</hi> of the Feaſt.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day, at the Church of S. <hi>Maria della Pace,</hi> they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins, and moreover innumerable Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and thus they have, during the whole <hi>Octave</hi> of the ſame Feaſt.</p>
                     <p>Moreover alſo the ſame day, at the Church of S. <hi>Maria de gli An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gioli,</hi> are the like Indulgences.</p>
                     <p>The day of the <hi>Octave</hi> of S. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> which is the ſixth day, at the Church of S. <hi>Peter</hi> is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the Diviſion of the Apoſtles, which is the ninth day, at S. <hi>Peters</hi> there are twelve thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> which is the fourteenth day, at the Church of S. <hi>Peter</hi> is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Quirico,</hi> which is the fifteenth day, at his Church there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Aleſſio,</hi> which is the ſeventeenth day, is a Station to his Church, and there they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, the ſame day, at the Church of S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Simphoraſa,</hi> which is the eighteenth day, at the Church of S. <hi>Angelo</hi> in <hi>Peſcaria,</hi> is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Margarita,</hi> which is the twentieth day, at her Church is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:152745:20"/>
                     <p>Moreover, the ſame day at <hi>Santa Croce</hi> are an hundred years In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Praſſede</hi> Virgin, which is the twenty firſt day, at her Church are ſix thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day, at the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> are two thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, the ſame day alſo at the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> it being the <hi>Octave</hi> of S. <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> there is a Plenary Indulgence granted by Pope <hi>Siſto</hi> the fourth.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> which is the twenty ſecond day, is a Station to her Church, and there they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins, granted by <hi>Clement</hi> the ſeventh, and <hi>Paul</hi> the fourth.</p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> the ſame day they have a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Celſo</hi> in <hi>Banchi,</hi> the ſame day alſo they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins, and moreover infinite Indulgences.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, the ſame day, at the Church of S. <hi>Lazarus,</hi> there are many Pardons.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Apollinare</hi> Martyr, which is the twenty third day, at his Church there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day, at the Church of S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> are an hundred years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Creſtina,</hi> Virgin and Martyr, which is the twenty fourth day, at the Church of S. <hi>Maria Maggiore</hi> there are forty years Indulgence; and at the Church of S. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> forty eight years.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>James</hi> Apoſtle, which is the twenty fifth day, is a Station to his Church, and there they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>At S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> the ſame day, there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, the ſame day, and in all the Feaſts of the Apoſtles, there is at the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and at the Church of S. <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>James,</hi> a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Anne,</hi> which is the twenty ſixth day, at her Church there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Pantaleone,</hi> which is the twenty ſeventy day, at his Church there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day, at the Church of S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> there are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Nazario</hi> and <hi>Celſo,</hi> which is the twenty eighth day, at the Church of <hi>Santa Croce,</hi> there are three hundred years Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:152745:20"/>
                     <p>The ſame day, at S. <hi>Maria de gli Angioli,</hi> is the like Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Martha,</hi> which is the twenty ninth day, at her Church there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day, at the Church of S. <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> there are five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Abdon</hi> and <hi>Sennen,</hi> which is the thirtieth day, at the Church of S. <hi>Mark,</hi> they have plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart__month">
                     <head>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ST.</head>
                     <p>THe day of S. <hi>Peter</hi> in <hi>Vincula,</hi> which is the firſt day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> is a Station to his Church, and there they have a plenary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of their ſins for eight days following.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day, at the Church of <hi>della Nonciata,</hi> they have a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> the ſame day, they have an Indulgence of twelve thouſand years, and of as many times forty days ſpace, and the forgiveneſs of the third part of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, at S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> the ſame day, they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The day of the Dedication of S. <hi>Maria de gli Angioli,</hi> or <hi>della Portiuncula,</hi> the which was the firſt Church of the Order of S. <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> at the Church of S. <hi>Maria Maggiore</hi> is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the finding out of S. <hi>Stephen,</hi> which is the third day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Laurence</hi> without the Wall, and there they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Domedico,</hi> which is the fourth day, is a Station to the Church of <hi>Minerva,</hi> and there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the Feaſt of S. <hi>Maria della Neve,</hi> which is the fifth day, at the Church of S. <hi>Maria Maggiore</hi> is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day, at the Church of S. <hi>Maria de gli Angioli,</hi> they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>Moreover alſo the ſame day, at S. <hi>Maria della Pace,</hi> they have a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the Transfiguration of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, which is the ſixth day, is a Station to S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> and there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at <hi>Santa Croce</hi> in <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> it being alſo the Feaſt of S. <hi>Siſto,</hi> there are very many Indulgences.</p>
                     <p>Alſo the ſame day, at S. <hi>Maria de gli Angioli,</hi> are the like Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences.</p>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:152745:21"/>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Ciriaco, Largo,</hi> and <hi>Smaragdo,</hi> which is the eighth day, at the Church of S. <hi>Ciriaco,</hi> they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day, at the Church of S. <hi>Sebaſtiano,</hi> are a thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Laurence,</hi> which is the tenth day, at the Church of S. <hi>Laurence</hi> without the Wall, they have an Indulgence of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years, and of as many times forty days ſpace, and a plenary remiſſion of their ſins; and it continueth thus during the <hi>Octave</hi> of the ſame Feaſt.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, in the ſaid Church, they have daily, during the ſaid <hi>Octave,</hi> one hundred fifty eight thouſand, and ſix hundred fifty eight years, and two hundred eighty five days, and any day, a thouſand years, and a Plenary Indulgence, and the remiſſion of the third part of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Clare,</hi> of the Order of S. <hi>Francis,</hi> which is the twelfth day, is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Sylveſter,</hi> and there they have plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day, at S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> is a Plenary Indulgence; and at <hi>Santa Croce</hi> an hundred years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Euſebio</hi> Confeſſor, which is the fourteenth day, at his Church there are a thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day, at S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> are a thouſand years Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Vigil</hi> of the Aſſumption of our Lady, at S. <hi>Maria del Popolo,</hi> at <hi>Veſpers,</hi> is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the Feaſt of the ſaid Aſſumption, which is the fifteenth day, is a Station to S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> and there they have a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years Indulgence, and a plenary remiſſion of their ſins; and thus it continueth the whole <hi>Octave.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>At S. <hi>Maria del Popolo</hi> is a Plenary Indulgence, and the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth daily as above, granted by Pope <hi>Siſto</hi> the fourth.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, the ſame day is a Plenary Indulgence at S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>At S. <hi>Maria Araceli,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>At S. <hi>Maria de gli Angioli,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And at S. <hi>Maria della Pace.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Moreover, at S. <hi>Spirito</hi> in <hi>Saſſia,</hi> the ſame day, are two thouſand years Indulgence; and thus it continueth, during the whole <hi>Octave,</hi> granted by Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the ſixth.</p>
                     <p>Note alſo, that from the ſaid Feaſt, until after the day of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152745:21"/>of our Lady, which is the eighth day of <hi>September,</hi> at S. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Maggiore</hi> they have any day twelve years Indulgence, and the forgiveneſs of the third part of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, at the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> the day of the ſaid Aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and every day during the <hi>Octave,</hi> there are eight hundred fifty one thouſand, one hundred ſixty two years, and an hundred days of Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Rocco,</hi> which is the ſixteenth day, at his Church there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Sunday</hi> after the <hi>Octave</hi> of the Aſſumption is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Maria de Araceli,</hi> and there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Lodovico</hi> Confeſſor, of the Order of S. <hi>Francis,</hi> which is the nineteenth day, is a Station to S. <hi>Maria de Araceli,</hi> and there they have remiſſion of all their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Anaſtatio</hi> Martyr, which is the twenty firſt day, is a Station to his Church, and there they have remiſſion of all their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Octave</hi> of the Aſſumption of our Lady, which is the twenty ſecond day, is a Station to S. <hi>Maria</hi> in <hi>Tranſtevere,</hi> and there is a Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Bartholomew</hi> Apoſtle, which is the twenty fourth day, is a Station to his Church, and there is a plenary remiſſion.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day, at S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> is the like Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, at S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, and at S. <hi>Philip</hi>'s and <hi>James</hi>'s, they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins; and ſo they have in every of the Feaſts of the Apoſtles.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Lodovico,</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> which is the twenty fifth day, is a Station to S. <hi>Luigi,</hi> belonging to the <hi>French,</hi> and there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Biſhop, which is the twenty eighth day, at his Church there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day, at S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> are a thouſand years Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the Decollation of S. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> which is the twenty ninth day, is a Station to his Church, and there is a Plenary Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day, at the Church of S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> is the like In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart__month">
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:152745:22"/>
                     <head>SEPTEMBER</head>
                     <p>THe day of S. <hi>Egidio</hi> Abbot, which is the firſt day of <hi>September,</hi> is a Station to his Church, and there is a Plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Vigil</hi> of the Nativity of our Lady, which is the ſeventh day, there is in the Evening, at the Church of S. <hi>Maria del Popolo,</hi> a Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the Nativity of our Lady, which is the eighth day, is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> and there they have a thouſand years Indulgence, and a plenary remiſſio of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, the ſame day at S. <hi>Maria Rotonda,</hi> they have an Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence Plenary, and an Indulgence of one hundred fifty nine thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſeven hundred and ninety years, and of one hundred eighty five days.</p>
                     <p>Alſo there is an Indulgence Plenary the ſame day at S. <hi>Maria de Araceli.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>At S. <hi>Maria</hi> in <hi>Via Lata.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>At S. <hi>Maria della Pace.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>At S. <hi>Maria de gli Angioli.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>At S. <hi>Maria del Popolo:</hi> And thus there is alſo, during the <hi>Octave</hi> of the ſame Feaſt, granted by Pope <hi>Siſto</hi> the fourth.</p>
                     <p>At S. <hi>Spirito</hi> in <hi>Saſſia,</hi> the ſame day, there are eight thouſand eight hundred years Indulgence; and thus there is daily, during the ſaid <hi>Octave.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Moreover, the ſame day is a Station to S. <hi>Maria di Loreto</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> where there is a Plenary Indulgence, both for the Living and Dead.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Adrian</hi> Martyr, which is the eighth day alſo, at the Church of S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> there are two hundred years In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Nicholas da Tolentino,</hi> which is the tenth day, is a Station to S. <hi>Maria del Popolo,</hi> and there they have plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day, at the Church of S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> is the like Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, the <hi>Sunday</hi> between the day of S. <hi>Nicholas da Tolentino,</hi> and its <hi>Octave,</hi> at the Church of S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> is a Plenary Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, granted by Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the ſeventh.</p>
                     <p>The Feaſt of the Exaltation of the <hi>Holy Croſs,</hi> which is the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day, is a Station to <hi>Santa Croce</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and there they have a thouſand and forty years, and the remiſſion of the third part
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152745:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>of their Sins, and one hundred fifty ſix thouſand ſixty four years, and forty five days of Indulgence, and moreover the forgiveneſs of their ſins during the Octave of the ſame Feaſt.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at S. <hi>Maria de gli Angioli,</hi> they have a plenary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of their ſins, and thus they have dayly during the Octave.</p>
                     <p>Moreover the ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>John Lateran</hi> in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory of <hi>Santa Croce,</hi> is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Moreover the ſame day alſo, at the moſt holy crucifix in the Church of S. <hi>Marcello,</hi> is a plenary Indulgence granted by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the thirteenth.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Eufemia Lucia,</hi> and <hi>Geminiano,</hi> at the Church of S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> are a thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Wedneſday</hi> after the Feaſt of the Holy Croſs, which is Ember-<hi>Wedneſday,</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Maria Maggiore;</hi> and there they have an Indulgence of eighteen thouſand years, and of eighteen thouſand times forty days ſpace, and the forgiveneſs of the third part of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Fryday</hi> after the ſaid <hi>Wedneſday</hi> is a Station to S. <hi>Apoſtolo,</hi> and there they have eighteen thouſand years Indulgence, and a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Saturday</hi> following is a Station to S. <hi>Peters,</hi> and there they have an Indulgence of twenty eight thouſand years, and of twenty eight thouſand times forty days ſpace, and the Remiſſion of the third part their ſins, and each delivereth a Soul from Purgatory.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Euſtachio</hi> and his company, which is the twentieth day, at his Church there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> are thirteen years In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Matthew</hi> Apoſtle and Evangeliſt, which is the twenty firſt day, is a Station to his Church, and there they have a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>Laurence</hi> they have an Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence plenary, and an hundred and thirty years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Moreover the ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and at the Church of S. <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>James,</hi> is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Coſmo</hi> and <hi>Damiano,</hi> which is the twenty-ſeventh day, at their Church there is a plenary Indulgence after the manner of <hi>Jubily</hi> granted by Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> is an Indulgence of ſeven thouſand years.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Michael,</hi> which is the twenty-ninth day, is a Station
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152745:23"/>to his Church, and there they have a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>At S. <hi>Angelo</hi> in <hi>Peſcaria</hi> the ſame day they have alſo a plenary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>Moreover the ſame day at S. <hi>Maggiore</hi> they have an Indulgence plenary, and one hundred fifty four thouſand nine hundred ninety one years, and two hundred and nine days of Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Girolamo,</hi> which is the thirtieth day, at the Church of S. <hi>Maria Maggiore</hi> they have a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins, and two thouſand years of Indulgence; and moreover two hundred fifty eight thouſand ſeven hundred and ninety years, and two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred eighty five days of Indulgence.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart__month">
                     <head>OCTOBER.</head>
                     <p>THe day of the Feaſt of the bleſſed Father <hi>Serafico</hi> a holy <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcan,</hi> which is the fourth day of <hi>October,</hi> is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Francis</hi> in <hi>Tranſtevere,</hi> and there they have a plenary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of their ſins; and thus they have dayly during the Octave of the Feaſt.</p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Paul</hi> the ſame day they have one hundred eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-five thouſand nine-hundred ſixty-eight years, and two hundred eightyfive days of Indulgence; and thus they have daily as above ſaid.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Caliſto</hi> Pope and Martyr, which is the fourteenth day, at the Church of S. <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> becauſe of the Cemitery of the ſaid Pope, where are buried one-hundred ſeventy four thouſand Martyrs, of which eighteen were Popes, there is a plenary indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The firſt ſunday after the Feaſt of the above-ſaid S. <hi>Caliſto,</hi> is a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to S. <hi>Maria</hi> in <hi>Tranſtevere.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Luke</hi> Evangeliſt, which is the eighteenth day, is a Station to his Church, and there they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at S. <hi>Maria Maggiere</hi> are a thouſand years indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Theodore,</hi> which is the twenty-third day, at his Church there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi> Apoſtles, which is the twenty-eight day, is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and there they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins, and the ſame they have in all the Feaſts of the Apoſtles.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>James,</hi> is the like Indulgence.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart__month">
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:152745:23"/>
                     <head>NOVEMBER</head>
                     <p>THe day of the Commemoration of all Saints, which is the firſt day of <hi>November,</hi> is a Station to S. <hi>Maria Rotonda,</hi> and there they have one hundred fifty five thouſand nine hundred ninety two years, and an hundred days Indulgence, and moreover an Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence plenary; and thus they have daily during the Octave of the ſame Feaſt.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at S. <hi>Spirito</hi> in <hi>Saſſia</hi> they have an Indulgence of three thouſand years, and of three thouſand times forty days ſpace, granted by Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the twelfth, and thus they have daily until after the day of S. <hi>Leonard,</hi> which is the ſixt day of this month.</p>
                     <p>Alſo the ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>Praſſede</hi> they have an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and twenty thouſand years, and an hundred and twenty times forty days ſpace, and the Remiſſion of the third part of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>And moreover at S. <hi>Babiana</hi> there are ſixty thouſand years Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the Commemoration of all the dead, which is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond day, is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Gregory,</hi> and there every one hath a plenary Remiſſion of his ſins; and thus he hath every day during the Octave of the Commemoration, and moreover he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livereth a Soul from Purgatory.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day alſo, and at the ſame Church, there are an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fifty four thouſand nine hundred ninety one years, and two hundred days of Indulgence; and thus there is dayly during the Octave.</p>
                     <p>Moreover the ſame day alſo at S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> is a plenary Indulgence, and thus there is daily during the Octave; and moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver each one taketh as aforeſaid a Soul from Purgatory.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day alſo at S. <hi>James</hi> in <hi>Auguſta</hi> is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Upon the Octave of any S. There is at S. <hi>Peters</hi> a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The day of the four <hi>Santi Coronati,</hi> which is the eight day, at their Church there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the Dedication of S. <hi>Salvatore,</hi> which is the ninth day, is a Station to S. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> and there they have a plenary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of their ſins; an hundred years, and three hundred days; and moreover one hundred fifty four thouſand ſix hundred eighty three years, and two hundred eighty five days of Indulgence.</p>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:152745:24"/>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Triphone,</hi> which is the tenth day, at his Church there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day alſo, they Celebrate the Feaſt of S. <hi>Reſpicio</hi> and <hi>Nin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fa,</hi> in which at the Church of S. <hi>Laurence</hi> there are very many Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Martin,</hi> which is the Eleventh day, at his Church there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at S. <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> are three hundred years, and three-hundred times forty days ſpace, of Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> the ſame day, they have a plenary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The day of the Dedication of S. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> which is the eighteenth day, is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and there they have a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins, and an Indulgence of an eleven thouſand years, and of an eleven thouſand times forty days ſpace, and the Remiſſion of the third part of their ſins; and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over one hundred fifty nine thouſand nine hundred ſixty four years, and two hundred eighty five days of Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>Paul</hi> they have an Indulgence of a thouſand years, and of a thouſand times forty days ſpace, and a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Daughter to the King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> at <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Croce</hi> are ten thouſand one hundred years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at S. <hi>Maria de gli Angioli</hi> are ten thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the preſentation of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which is the twenty firſt day, is a Station to S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> and there they have a thouſand years Indulgence, and moreover a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>Maria della Pace</hi> the ſame day is a plenary In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Cecilia,</hi> which is the twenty ſecond day, at her Church there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at S. <hi>Maria</hi> in <hi>Araceli,</hi> are twenty years Indulgence, and moreover an Indulgence of one hundred fifty nine thouſand ſeven hundred and ninety years, and two hundred eighty five days.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Clement</hi> Pope, which is the twenty third day, is a Station to his Church, and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at S. <hi>Peters</hi> are one hundred fifty eight thouſand nine hundred ſixty ſix years, and two hundred and fifty days of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</p>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:152745:24"/>
                     <p>Alſo the ſame day being the day of S. <hi>Felicita</hi> Martyr, at <hi>Santa Croce</hi> are forty years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Criſogono,</hi> which is the twenty fourth day, is a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his Church, and there they have plenary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at S. <hi>Maria Maggiore</hi> are a thouſand years indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Saturnino,</hi> which is the twenty ninth day, at the Church of S. <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> are an hundred years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Andrew</hi> Apoſtle, which is the thirtieth day, is a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and there is a plenary Indulgence, as there is alſo in all the Feaſts of the Apoſtles; and moreover they have there a thouſand years Indulgence, and the Remiſſion of the third part of their ſins, and alſo one hundred fifty nine thouſand nine hundred ſeventy nine years, and forty five days of Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>At the Church of S. <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> the ſame day they have a ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>At S. <hi>Andrews</hi> without <hi>Porta del Popolo,</hi> a Church built by Pope <hi>Julio</hi> the third, is a plenary Indulgence both for the Living and the Dead.</p>
                     <p>Moreover the ſame day at S. <hi>Catharine de Fornari</hi> there is a plenary Jubily granted by Pope <hi>Julio</hi> the third.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart__liturgical_season">
                     <head>The Indulgences in the four Sundays of <hi>Advent.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe firſt Sunday of <hi>Advent,</hi> is a Station to S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> and there they have twenty eight thouſand years Indulgence, and moreover the forgiveneſs of the third part of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at S. <hi>Peters</hi> they have a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond Sunday of <hi>Advent</hi> is a Station to <hi>Santa Croce</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and there they have eleven thouſand years Indulgence, and a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at S. <hi>Maria de gli Angioli</hi> is the like Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The third Sunday of <hi>Advent</hi> is a Station to S. <hi>Peters,</hi> and there they have twenty eight thouſand years Indulgence, and twenty eight thouſand times forty days ſpace, and a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The fourth Sunday of <hi>Advent</hi> is alſo a Station to S. <hi>Peters,</hi> and there they have a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:152745:25"/>
                     <p>The ſame day at S. <hi>Apoſtolo</hi> they have twenty eight thouſand years Indulgence, and a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart__month">
                     <head>DECEMBER.</head>
                     <p>THe day of S. <hi>Babina</hi> Virgin and Martyr, which is the ſecond day of <hi>December,</hi> is a Station to her Church, and there they have a plenary remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at S. <hi>Maria Maggiore</hi> are nine thouſand years Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Barbara</hi> Virgin and Martyr, which is the fourth day, at her Church there are ſixteen thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>At <hi>Santa Croce</hi> the ſame day there are a thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Saba</hi> Abbot, which is the firſt day, at his Church there is a plenary Remiſſion of every ones ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at S. <hi>Peters</hi> are an hundred years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Nicholas</hi> Biſhop, which is the ſixt day, is a Station to S. <hi>Nicholas delle Carceri,</hi> and there they have a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins, and moreover three hundred years, and three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times forty days ſpace of Indulgence; and alſo an Indulgence plenary.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at <hi>Santa Croce</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is a plenary Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day alſo at S. <hi>Maria de gli Angioli</hi> is the like Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> which is the ſeventh day, at his Church there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at S. <hi>Peters</hi> are a thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the Conception of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> which is the eight day, is a Station to S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> and there they have a thouſand years Indulgence, and a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at S. <hi>Maria Rotonda,</hi> and alſo at S. <hi>Maria de gli An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gioli,</hi> is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Moreover likewiſe there is a plenary Indulgence the ſame day, and likewiſe daily during the Octave of the ſame Feaſt, theſe at three enſuing Churches; to wit,</p>
                     <p>S. <hi>Maria</hi> in <hi>Araceli.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>S. <hi>Maria del Popolo,</hi> and</p>
                     <p>S. <hi>Maria della Pace.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Lucia</hi> Virgin and Martyr, which is the thirteenth
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152745:25"/>day, at her Church they have a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Wedneſday</hi> after S. <hi>Lucia</hi> being Ember <hi>Wedneſday</hi> is a Station to S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> and there they have twenty eight thouſand years Indulgence, and twenty eight thouſand times forty days ſpace, and the Remiſſion of the third part of their ſins, and moreover a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Fryday</hi> following the ſaid <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> is a Station to S. <hi>Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolo,</hi> and there they have ten thouſand years Indulgence, and a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>Upon <hi>Saturday</hi> in the ſame week, it being Ember <hi>Saturday,</hi> is a Station to S. <hi>Peters,</hi> and there they have twenty eight thouſand years, and twenty eight thouſand times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Thomas</hi> Apoſtle which is the twenty firſt day, at his Church they have a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>Paul</hi> is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day alſo at the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and alſo at the Church of S. <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>James,</hi> is a plenary Indulgence; and thus there is alſo in all the Feaſts of the Apoſtles.</p>
                     <p>The Vigil of the Nativity of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which is the twenty fourth day, is a Station to S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> and there they have twenty eight thouſand years, and twenty eight thouſand times forty days ſpace of Indulgence, and the Remiſſion of the third part of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>The Night of Chriſts Nativity is a Station to the Chappel of <hi>Preſepio</hi> in the Church of S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> and there at the ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the firſt Maſs, they have a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>At S. <hi>Maria</hi> in <hi>Araceli</hi> the ſame Night they have a plenary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>Upon the day of the Nativity of Chriſt, which is the twenty fift day, at the ſecond Maſs, is a Station to S. <hi>Anaſtaſia,</hi> and there they have an Indulgence of twenty eight thouſand years, and of twenty eight thouſand times forty days ſpace, and a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>At the third Maſs, upon the day of Chriſt's Nativity is a Station to S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> and there they have one hundred fifty nine thouſand ſeven hundred and ninety years, and two hundred eighty five days of Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Alſo upon the day of Chriſts Nativity is a Station to the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of <hi>Preſepio</hi> in S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> and there they have an Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of twenty eight thouſand years, and of twenty eight thouſand times forty days ſpace, and a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:152745:26"/>
                     <p>In each of the three Maſſes upon the day of Chriſts Nativity, at the Church of S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> is an Indulgence plenary, and moreover a thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Alſo the ſame day at S. <hi>Maria</hi> in <hi>Araceli,</hi> are all the ſaid Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences. And at S. <hi>Maria de gli Angioli</hi> is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Anaſtaſia</hi> Martyr, which is alſo the day of Chriſts Nativity, at the Church of S. <hi>Maria Maggiore</hi> are a thouſand years Indulgences.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Stephen Proto</hi>-Martyr, which is the twenty ſixt day, is a Station to S. <hi>Laurence</hi> without the wall, where repoſeth his holy Body, and there each hath a plenary Remiſſion of his ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at S. <hi>Stephen</hi> in <hi>Monte Celio,</hi> they have one hundred fifty four thouſand nine hundred ninety one years, and two hundred days of Indulgence, and a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins.</p>
                     <p>Alſo the ſame day at the Church of the ſaid S. <hi>Laurence,</hi> they have an Indulgence of an hundred years, and of an hundred times forty days ſpace, and the Remiſſion of the third part of their ſins: and thus they have daily during the Octave of the ſame Feaſt.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>John</hi> Apoſtle and Evangeliſt, which is the twenty ſeventh day, is a Station to S. <hi>Maria Maggiore,</hi> and there is a plena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Remiſſion of every ones ſins.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day alſo is a Station to the Church of S. <hi>John</hi> Lateran, and there they have an Indulgence of twenty eight thouſand years, and of twenty eight thouſand times forty days ſpace, and a plenary Indulgence, and the delivering of a Soul from Purgatory, and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over Infinite Indulgences.</p>
                     <p>Moreover alſo the ſame day, both at the Church of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and at the Church of S. <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>James,</hi> they have a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins. And at the Church of S. <hi>Paul</hi> there are an hundred years Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The day of the Holy Innocents, which is the twenty eight day, is a Station to S. <hi>Pauls,</hi> and there they have an Indulgence of fifteen thouſand years, and of fifteen thouſand times forty days ſpace, and a plenary Remiſſion of their ſins; and more over there are one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fifty five thouſand two hundred ninety one years, and two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred days of Indnigence.</p>
                     <p>The day of S. <hi>Silveſter,</hi> which is the thirty firſt day, is a Station to his Church, and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>The ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>John Lateran</hi> is an Indulgence plenary, and moreover ten thouſand years of Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>Alſo the ſame day at the Church of S. <hi>Maria</hi> in <hi>Tranſtevere,</hi> there
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152745:26"/>are one hundred fifty eight thouſand nine hundred fifty eight years and two hundred eighty five days of Indulgence.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Moreover there are many other great Indulgences any day in divers places and Churches of</hi> Rome, <hi>and in the Dedication of the Altars, and of the Churches, and in divers times, places, and Feaſts of the Saints, which do greatly increaſe the aforeſaid Indulgences.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>CLASSE III.</hi> The Indulgences in the holy Land, which are gained not only by devout Pilgrims, and ſuch others as viſit the ſacred places where they are to be obtained, but alſo by thoſe inveſted with the habit of the holy order of the Servants of our Lady.</head>
               <div type="subpart__place">
                  <head>The Indulgences at Mount <hi>Sion.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN the place where Chriſt made his laſt Supper, is a plenary In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the Chappel of S. <hi>Thomas</hi> Apoſtle, where our Lord appeared to him, is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the Chappel where the Holy Ghoſt deſcended the Day of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecoſt, is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where our Lady died is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where S. <hi>Matthias</hi> was elected Apoſtle, there are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven years and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where S. <hi>James</hi> the Apoſtle was choſen the firſt Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> there are ſeven years and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the Chappel where S. <hi>John Evangeliſt</hi> ſaid Maſs to our Lady, are ſeven years, and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where the holy Apoſtles ſeparated themſelves for to go to Preach the Goſpel to the whole world, are ſeven years and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where was Tranſlated the body of S. <hi>Stephen</hi> Proto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>martyr, are ſeven years, and ſeven times forty days ſpace of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the Chappel, that formerly was the Kitchen in which the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152745:27"/>Paſchal Lamb was roſted for Chriſt, are ſeven years, and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the entrance of the houſe of <hi>Caiphas,</hi> where a Maid Portreſs ſaid to <hi>Peter, Thou waſt with Jeſus Chriſt of Galilee,</hi> are ſeven years and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the midſt of the ſame Houſe, where <hi>Peter</hi> denied Chriſt, are ſeven years, and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>Near to that Houſe is a place where the Cock Crew, and there are ſeven years, and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In a certain place in the ſaid Houſe of <hi>Caiphas,</hi> where Chriſt the night before he ſuffered ſtood after he was taken till morning, are ſeven years, and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>Near to the ſaid houſe is a place unto which our Lady came, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding that her Son was taken, fainted; and there are ſeven years, and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>Near to the ſame Houſe is a place where the <hi>Jews</hi> would have took the body of our Lady, when ſhe was carried to burial; and there are ſeven years and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>Upon the ſaid Mount Sion is the place in which they beheaded S. <hi>James</hi> the great, and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart__place">
                  <head>The Indulgences at Mount <hi>Calvary</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AT the place where the Croſs of Chriſt was planted, and where he was crucified, is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>At the place where <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> offered Bread and Wine, are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven years, and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>At the place where <hi>Abraham</hi> would have ſacrificed his Son <hi>Iſaac,</hi> are ſeven years, and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>At the place where our Lord was taken from the Croſs and put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Boſom of our Lady, is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>At the holy Sepulchre is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>At a certain Chappel, near to the place where Chriſt was crucified, is a certain Ladder, and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>Under the Rock where our Lord was crucified, is a Chappel, in which S. <hi>Helena</hi> found the Croſs of Chriſt, and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In another Chappel is a certain pillar upon which Chriſt ſat after he had been Crowned with Thorns; and there are ſeven years and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In another Chappel, where they did caſt lots upon Chriſts gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152745:27"/>are ſeven years, and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                  <p>In a certain Den, where Chriſt was put whilſt his Crucifiers made ready his Croſs, are ſeven years, and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the Garden where our Lord after his Reſurrection appeared to S. <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> are ſeven years, and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where S. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> fainted in the Garden, are ſeven years, and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the ſame place is a certain Concavity, like to a Window, where is a part of the Pillar at which Chriſt was whipped; and there are ſeven years, and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the Chappel where the Croſs was found, is upon the Altar a part of the Croſs, and there are ſeven years, and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the ſaid Chappel is a place, in which after they had found the holy Croſs, laying the ſame upon a Woman departed, it raiſed her from the dead; and there are ſeven years and ſeven times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart__place">
                  <head>Indulgences in the City of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AT the entrance of the City of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Pilgrims obtain forty years and forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>At the golden Gate, by which Chriſt entred upon Palm-Sunday, is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In a certain Houſe where they ſay was born the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the Houſe where S. <hi>John</hi> Evangeliſt was born, are ſeven years and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the Houſe of the Woman called <hi>Veronica,</hi> are ſeven years, and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the Houſe of <hi>Simeon</hi> the Prophet, are ſeven years, and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the Temple of <hi>Solomon,</hi> where our Ladie preſented Chriſt, is a plenarie Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where the Angel deſcended and troubled the waters, are ſeven years, and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where our Lord had wont to preach, are ſeven years, and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:152745:28"/>
                  <p>In the place where Chriſt illuminated the man born blind, are ſeven years, and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>Near to a certain Stone, where they ſay our Lord healed many ſick People, are ſeven years, and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the Tower of <hi>David,</hi> Chriſt being of his Race, are ſeven years and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the Dining-Room, where Chriſt waſhed the Feet of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, are ſeven years, and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                  <p>At the houſe of S. <hi>Lazarus</hi> and his Siſters, in the way by which they took Chriſt to be crucified, are ſeven years, and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where they ſay our Lord fell down under the Croſs, are ſeven years, and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where they forced <hi>Simon</hi> of <hi>Cirene</hi> to carrie the Croſs of Chriſt, are ſeven years, and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where are two white Stones, where Chriſt being wearied through the weight of his Croſs did make a little pauſe or reſt; are ſeven years and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where our Ladie, ſeeing Chriſt with the Croſs, did fall down as dead, are ſeven years, and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where Chriſt appeared to his Mother <hi>Mary,</hi> after his Reſurrection, are ſeven years, and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where Chriſt appeared to the three <hi>Maries,</hi> and ſaid <hi>All Hail,</hi> are ſeven years, and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</p>
                  <p>In a Church which was the Houſe where the bleſſed Virgin inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited after Chriſts Aſcenſion, are ſeven years, and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the Oratory where our Ladie had wont to do her Devotions, are ſeven years, and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart__place">
                  <head>Indulgences in the Valley of <hi>Shiloe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN the place called <hi>Acheldemach,</hi> bought with the thirty pence with the which Chriſt was ſold, there are ſeven years, and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:152745:28"/>
                  <p>In the place where Chriſt commanded the Clouds to depart thence, to the end he might ſee, are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where S. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet was ſawed a-ſunder with a Wooden Saw, are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the ſame Valley is a certain Den, in the which S. <hi>Peter</hi> wept when he had denyed Chriſt, and there are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In this Valley alſo is a certain Fountain in the which the Bleſſed Virgin waſhed the Linnens of Jeſus Chriſt, he being a little one, when ſhe came with him to the <hi>Temple;</hi> and there are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart__place">
                  <head>Indulgences at the Brook <hi>Cedron.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AT this Brook was the Wood for a certain time with the which was made the Croſs of Chriſt, and there are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the Garden called <hi>Gethſemane,</hi> where Chriſt, the Night he was taken, left eight of his Apoſtles the whilſt he prayed, are ſeven years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where Chriſt at the ſame time prayed thrice, and did ſweat Blood, are ſeven Years and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In a certain Den, where S. <hi>James Alpheus</hi> wept after that Chriſt was taken, vowing that he would neither eat nor drink until he ſaw him riſen again from the Dead, are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>Near to this Brook <hi>Cedron</hi> is the place where was born S. <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> the Father of S. <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, and there are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart__place">
                  <head>Indulgences in the Valley of <hi>Jehoſaphat.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN the Valley of <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> is the Sepulchre of our Lady, and there is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>Between the ſaid Sepulchre and the City of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is the place where S. <hi>Stephen</hi> was ſtoned, and there are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart__place">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:152745:29"/>
                  <head>Indulgences at Mount <hi>Olivet.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AT the foot of Mount <hi>Olivet</hi> is a little Village called <hi>Bethphage,</hi> from which Chriſt did ride upon an Aſs to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and there are fifteen Years, and fifteen times forty Daies ſpace of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                  <p>At the other ſide of the Mount, near <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> is the place where Chriſt beholding the City wept over it, and there are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>Upon the ſaid Mount, where our Lord taught the Apoſtles to pray, and Compoſed the <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where our Lord Preached the Beatitudes is the like Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>Upon the ſame Mount an Angel (they ſay) declared to the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin the Paſſage of Chriſt, bearing a Palm, and there are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where Chriſt viſibly aſcended into Heaven, is a plenary Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>Upon the ſame Mount is a place where the Apoſtles after the coming of the Holy Ghoſt, compoſed the Creed, and there are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of indulgence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart__place">
                  <head>The Indulgences at <hi>Bethany.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN the Houſe of <hi>Martha</hi> who lodged Chriſt, are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the Houſe of <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the midſt of the ſame Houſe is the place where <hi>Mary</hi> ſaid to Chriſt, <hi>Lord, if thou hadſt been here,</hi> &amp;c. and there are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where <hi>Lazarus</hi> was buried, and raiſed from the Dead, is a plenarie indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the Houſe of <hi>Simon</hi> the Leper, where <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> anointed the Head of Chriſt, are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of indulgence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart__place">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:152745:29"/>
                  <head>The Indulgences at <hi>Bethlehem.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AT the Houſe where Chriſt was born, is a Plenary indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where Chriſt being born was wrapt up in Swadling Clothes is a plenary indulgence.</p>
                  <p>At the Altar where Jeſus Chriſt was Circumciſed is a plenary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the Houſe where the three Wiſe-men adored Chriſt, he being an Infant, are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where the Star vaniſhed from the Wiſe men, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had ſeen in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and which had conducted them to <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</p>
                  <p>In a certain Chappel, where are the Sepulchres of the Holy Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents, are ſeven Years and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                  <p>Moreover in a certain Church, entituled, <hi>The Church of the Bleſſed Virgin,</hi> where the Angels appeared to our Lady, ſhewing her the way to <hi>Egypt,</hi> to the end ſhe might fly thither with her Infant Jeſus, are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where the Angels appeared to the Shepheards ſinging <hi>Gloria in Excelſis Deo,</hi> are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of indulgence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart__place">
                  <head>The Indulgences at <hi>Nazareth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN the place where the Bleſſed Virgin was ſaluted by the Angel, is a plenary indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the Houſe of S. <hi>Joachim</hi> the Father of the Bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> at which is a certain Monaſtery, are ſeven years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of indulgence.</p>
                  <p>At a certain Fountain, from which Chriſt, being a little one, had wont to fetch Water and carry to his Mother, are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the the Houſe to which our Lady, being a little one, went to School to learn to read, are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of indulgence.</p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:152745:30"/>
                  <p>In the Houſe where were born S. <hi>James Thadeus,</hi> and S. <hi>John</hi> Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, are ten Years, and thirty times forty Daies ſpace of indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart__place">
                  <head>The Indulgences in the Mountainous Parts of <hi>Judea.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN a Church which was formerly the Houſe of <hi>Zachary,</hi> the Father of S. <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, where the Bleſſed Virgin ſaluted <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> and in which was born S. <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, are ſeven Years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the place where <hi>Zachary</hi> writ the name of his Son <hi>John,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God of</hi> Iſrael, &amp;c. are ſeven years, and ſeven times forty daies ſpace of indulgence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart__place">
                  <head>The Indulgences in the Valley of <hi>Hebron.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN the place where they ſay was buried <hi>Adam,</hi> our firſt Father, are ſeven years, and ſeven times forty Daies ſpace of indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                  <p>In the ſame Valley, in a certain Den, in which lyeth buried <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> are ſeven years, and ſeven times forty daies ſpace of indulgence.</p>
                  <p>Moreover in a certain place therein, where the Wood grew with which was made the Croſs of Chriſt, are twenty years, and twenty times forty daies ſpace of indulgence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart__place">
                  <head>The Indulgences at <hi>Galilee.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN the Deſart, wherein Chriſt faſted fortie daies, is a plenarie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</p>
                  <p>On the Mount upon which the Devil conducted Chriſt, are ſeven Years, and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the deſart, where S. <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt did Penance, are ſeven Years, and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of indulgence.</p>
                  <p>In the River <hi>Jordan,</hi> where Chriſt was Baptiſed, is a plenary indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
                  <p>Beſide the River <hi>Jordan</hi> is a certain Monaſterie, in which is a little piece of the Croſs of Chriſt, and there are ſeven Years, and ſeven times for tie daies ſpace of indulgence.</p>
                  <p>There is alſo another Monaſterie of S. <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, and there are ſeven years, and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of indulgence.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:152745:30"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CLASSE IV.</hi> The Indulgences at S. <hi>James</hi> of <hi>Galitia</hi> in <hi>Compoſtella,</hi> the which are gained not only by holy Pilgrims, and ſuch others devoutly viſiting the ſame Church, but alſo by thoſe of the holy order of the Servants of S. <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt, whatſoever perſon ſhall at any time go to S. <hi>James</hi> of <hi>Galitia,</hi> obtaineth the Remiſſion of the third part of his ſins.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly, Whoſoever goeth to viſit the ſaid Church, and going, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning, or in his ſtay there, happeneth to die, ſo it be with true Contrition for his errors, hath a plenary Remiſſion of his ſins.</p>
               <p n="3">3dly, Everie one that goeth in the proceſſion which they make upon <hi>Sunday</hi> in the ſame Church, hath for everie proceſſion and conſecration fortie daies Indulgence, and the ſame he hath each day in the Week, until the next <hi>Sunday</hi> enſuing, and moreover he hath an Indulgence of three hundred daies, and the forgiveneſs of the third part of his ſins.</p>
               <p n="4">4thly, In the Feaſt of the Dedication of the ſame Church, and in the Vigil and Feaſt of S. <hi>James,</hi> they have ſix hundred daies Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and a Remiſſion of the third part of their ſins.</p>
               <p n="5">5thly, Every one that hearkeneth to the Maſs of an Arch-biſhop, or of a Cardinal, at the Altar of S. <hi>James,</hi> hath ſix hundred daies of Indulgence, and the Remiſſion of the third part of his ſins.</p>
               <p n="6">6thly, <hi>Caliſto</hi> the Pope hath granted, that when the Feaſt of S. <hi>James</hi> happeneth to be celebrated upon a <hi>Sunday,</hi> all the ſame year, whoſoever goeth on Pilgrimage, truly penitent and confeſſed, ſhall be abſolved from all his ſins.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>CLASSE V.</hi> The Indulgences granted by divers Popes to thoſe that ſhall uſe certain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions; all which, as well as to others, appertain to the Brothers and Siſters of the holy order of the Servants of S. <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO thoſe that ſhall ſay the Divine Office, and the Cannonical hours, for any time they ſhall ſay the ſame, <hi>Leo</hi> the eleventh hath granted the forgiveneſs of the third part of their ſins, and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> the fifth hath granted an hundred daies Indulgence.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:152745:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall ſay the Office for the Dead, or the ſeven Pſalms, or the Gradual, <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth hath granted a plenarie In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall ſay the Pſalmes of the paſſion, the which are ten, the firſt whereof begineth with <hi>Deus Deus meus reſpice in me,</hi> and the laſt with <hi>In te Domine ſperavi; Leo</hi> the tenth hath granted a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> plenary Indulgence.</p>
               <p>They are called the Pſalmes of the Paſſion, becauſe it is believed that Chriſt ſaid the ſame in his mind upon the Croſs, for the firſt ſpeech of the ſeven he then uttered, he ſpake the beginning of the firſt of the ſaid Pſalmes, ſaying, <hi>Deus, Deus meus:</hi> and the laſt ſpeech which he made, which was, <hi>In manus tuas Domine commendo ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum meum,</hi> is found in the laſt of the ſaid Pſalmes, <hi>In te Domine ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſay the Pſalmes, the <hi>Antiphon,</hi> the <hi>Verſicle,</hi> and the Prayer of the name of <hi>Jeſus, Leo</hi> the tenth hath granted a plenarie Indulgence.</p>
               <p>They are called the Pſalmes of the name of Jeſus, becauſe the letters wherewith they begin, anſwer to the name of Jeſus; the firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with an <hi>J,</hi> the ſecond with an <hi>E,</hi> the third with an <hi>S, &amp;c.</hi> In ſaying whereof, firſt they ſay the <hi>Antiphon,</hi> to wit, <hi>In nomine Jeſu.</hi> Afterward they ſay the firſt of the ſaid Pſalmes, <hi>viz. Jubilate Deo omnis Terra;</hi> next they ſay the ſecond of the ſaid Pſalmes, namely, <hi>Exaudiat te Dominus;</hi> then they ſay the third of the ſaid Pſalmes; to wit, <hi>Salvum me fac Deus;</hi> then the fourth, which is, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſquequò Domine Obliviſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris me;</hi> Next the fifth, namely, <hi>Saepe Expugnaverunt me à ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventute mea.</hi> After the Pſalmes they ſay the <hi>Antiphon,</hi> In <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Jeſu omne genu flectatur, Coeleſtium, Terreſtrium, &amp; Infernorum, quia Dominus Jeſus Chriſtus in gloria eſt Dei Patris.</hi> Then they ſay the <hi>verſicle, Sit nomen Domini Benedictum,</hi> afterward they Anſwer, <hi>Ante ſolem permanet nomen ejus.</hi> Then they ſay, <hi>Oremus,</hi> and laſtly they ſay, <hi>Omnipotens ſempiterne Deus, dirige Actus noſtros in Beneplacito tuo, ut in nomine Dilecti filii tui mereamur bonis operibus abundare. Per eundem Chriſtum Dominum noſtrum,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall ſay one <hi>Miſerere</hi> before an Altar, <hi>Siſto</hi> the fourth hath granted all the Indulgences that are that day in <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Julio</hi> the ſecond hath adjoined, that ſaying every day one <hi>Miſerere</hi> with the prayer for the Pope, <hi>Deus omnium fidelium Paſtor &amp; Rector,</hi> &amp;c. ſhall obtain all the Indulgences that are to be had in the whole world.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall ſay fifteen Pater-Noſters, and fifteen <hi>Ave-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria's,</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:152745:31"/>in memory of the Wounds of Chriſt, <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth hath granted fifteen thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall ſay fifteen <hi>Pater-Noſter's,</hi> and fifteen <hi>Ave-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria's,</hi> for thoſe that are in mortal ſin, <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth hath granted for any time they ſhall ſay the ſame, the Remiſſion of the third part of their ſins.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall ſay five <hi>Pater-Noſter's</hi> and five <hi>Ave Maria's,</hi> praying for the happy Eſtate of the Holy Church, <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth hath granted all the Indulgences that are that day in <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall ſay five <hi>Pater-Noſter's</hi> and five <hi>Ave-Maria's,</hi> in honour and memory of the five Wounds of Chriſt, <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth hath granted ten thouſand years, and ten thouſand days of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall ſay once in the day one <hi>Pater-Noſter,</hi> and at the end thereof three times Jeſu, <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth hath granted three thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall ſay an <hi>Ave-Maria</hi> when they FART, <hi>John</hi> the Twenty Second hath granted forty days Indulgence.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall ſay the Crown of our Lord, which contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thirty three <hi>Pater-Noſter's</hi> and thirty three <hi>Ave-Maria's,</hi> in memory of the years of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Julio</hi> the Second, and <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth, have granted a plenary Indulgence.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall ſay the Crown of our Lady, the which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth ſixty three <hi>Ave-Maria's</hi> and ſeven <hi>Pater-Noſters, Leo</hi> the Tenth hath granted a plenary Indulgence. This Crown they are wont to ſay all over <hi>Italy,</hi> but out of <hi>Italy</hi> they uſe to ſay for the Crown of our Lady ſeventy three <hi>Ave-Maria's,</hi> and eight <hi>Pater Noſter's,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> the Twenty Second, hath granted to thoſe that ſhall ſay this Crown, a plenary Indulgence.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall ſay the Crown of our Lady the day of S. <hi>John ante Portam Latinam,</hi> which is the ſixth day of <hi>May, Leo</hi> the Tenth hath granted they ſhall thereby deliver a Soul from Purgatory, and the like he hath granted they ſhall do, ſaying the ſaid Crown the day of S. <hi>John</hi> Evangeliſt, which is the twenty ſeventh day of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall ſay the Roſary of the Bleſſed Virgin, <hi>Siſto</hi> the Fourth hath granted for every fiftieth, five years and five times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall ſay the Maſs of the moſt holy Roſary, or hearken to one of the ſaid Maſſes, <hi>Paul</hi> the Third hath granted, as many Indulgences as if they ſhould ſay the Roſary a whole Week,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152745:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>which would come to eighty eight years, twenty two times forty days ſpace, and an hundred and fifty days; and Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Thirteenth hath granted them a plenary Indulgence, and the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of a Soul from Purgatory.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall ſay or hear the Maſs of the Conception, <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth hath granted a plenary Indulgence.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall ſay in honour of the Bleſſed Virgin ſome one of theſe Hims, to wit, <hi>Quem Terra Pontus,</hi> or, <hi>O Glorioſa Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> or the Verſicle <hi>Maria Mater gratiae, Alexander</hi> the Sixth hath granted for every time they ſay the ſame, ten years Indulgence.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that bow at the name of Jeſus, and at the Verſicle <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Patri, &amp; Filio, &amp; Spiritui Sancto, John</hi> the Twenty Second hath granted for any time they do the ſame, forty days Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall kneel, or bow the knee, when they ſay, <hi>Te ergo Quaeſumus famulis tuis ſubveni,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Benedict</hi> the Thirteenth hath granted three times forty days ſpace of Indulgence; and to thoſe that ſhall bow the Head at the Speech of the Preface in the Maſs, <hi>Gratias agamus Domino Deo noſtro,</hi> an hundred days Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that Communicate, <hi>Innocent</hi> the Eighth, and <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth, have granted a plenary Indulgence.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that by reaſon of Sickneſs, or other juſt Impediment cannot ſay the Canonical Hours, or the <hi>Ave-Maria's,</hi> or the <hi>Pater-Noſter's</hi> belonging to their Rule, <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth hath granted that ſaying a Hymne, or a <hi>Pater-Noſter,</hi> or any other thing, according to the judgment of their Prelate or Corrector, they ſhall ſatisfie as if they had ſaid the Hours Canonical. And the ſame Pope hath grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that if any one, ſaying his Office in the Quire, or in the Paſſage, or any other place, did not, by reaſon of Idleneſs, Negligence, Malice, or a wandring mind, ſpeak his words intirely out, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely utter them, ſaying a <hi>Pater-Noſter,</hi> or an Hymne, or a <hi>Salva Regina,</hi> or other thing impoſed by his Prelate and Superiour, he ſhall make ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that are ſick and infirm and cannot Faſt, <hi>Siſta</hi> the Fourth hath granted that they are not bound. And <hi>Innocent</hi> the Eighth hath granted they may gain any Indulgence in the Infirmacy, in the Cell, or in Bed, ſaying five <hi>Pater-Noſter's,</hi> and five <hi>Ave-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria's,</hi> with an Intention to gain the ſame Indulgence. And <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth hath granted, that ſaying a Pſalm, or an Hymne of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin, or of our Lord, they ſhall have the Indulgence of the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152745:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>Crown of our Lord, or of our Lady; and likewiſe <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth hath granted, that if any one be troubled with a Feaver or other Malady at the time of the Canonical Hour, ſo that he cannot obſerve it, ſaying the Pſalms, the Hymnes, the <hi>Pater-Noſters,</hi> or any other thing, at the judgment of the Superiour, he ſhall make ſatisfaction. And <hi>Eugenio</hi> the Fourth, and <hi>Martin</hi> the Fifth, have confirmed the ſame, and moreover communicated it to the old and impotent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>CLASSE VI.</hi> The Indulgences granted to the Parents, Founders, Protectors, Favourites, and Benefactors of the Holy Order of the Servants of S. <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO the Father and Mother of each Religious Perſon of this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Order of the Servants, <hi>Caliſto</hi> the Third hath granted a plenary Indulgence in their life time, and after their death, the ſame in Purgatory, by way of ſuffrage.</p>
               <p>To the Tutors and Defenders of the Order of the Servants, <hi>Nicholas</hi> the Fourth hath granted an Indulgence of forty years, <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norio</hi> the Third of twenty five years and twenty days; <hi>Clement</hi> the Fourth of twenty five years and 120 days; <hi>Boniface</hi> the Eighth of twenty five years, and an hundred and twenty days; <hi>Innocent</hi> the Fourth of twenty five years, and an hundred and twenty days; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the Fifth of twenty five years, and an hundred and twenty days; and <hi>Leo</hi> the Fourth of ſeven years, and twelve times forty days ſpace.</p>
               <p>To all that are to this Holy Order of the Servants either Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates, Procurators, Phyſicians, or their Subſtitutes, <hi>Martin</hi> the Fourth hath granted for every year they are thus, an hundred years Indulgence: And <hi>Innocent</hi> the Eighth hath granted to them, their Children, their Brothers, their Siſters, their Wives, and their Parents, ſaying five <hi>Pater-Noſter's,</hi> and five <hi>Ave-Maria's</hi> for the happy Eſtate of the Holy Church, the Indulgences in all the Stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and all other Indulgences granted to the Brothers and Siſters of this Holy Order.</p>
               <p>To all of the Order of the ſervants that are Prieſts, or are in any other of the ſeven holy orders, <hi>John</hi> the twenty third hath granted the Ommiſſion and neglect of the Canonical hours, and Divine Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices.</p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>John</hi> the twentie third hath communicated all the good
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152745:33"/>works and ſuffrages of the Brothers and Siſters of this Order to the Souls of their dead Benefactors.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>CLASSE VII.</hi> The Indulgences granted to all that are Faithful and devout to the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Siſters of the Holy Order of the Servants of S. <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO thoſe that hear the Divine Offices in the Church of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, <hi>Honorio</hi> the Third hath given an Indulgence of eighty days; <hi>Boniface</hi> the Eighth of eighty days; <hi>Clement</hi> the Fifth of eighty days; <hi>Alexander</hi> the Fourth of three hundred and twenty days; <hi>Innocent</hi> the Fourth of two days; and <hi>Gregory</hi> the Fifth of two days; all which make one year and twenty days.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall hear a Sermon of a Prieſt of the Servants, <hi>Honorius</hi> the Third, <hi>Boniface</hi> the Eighth, <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third, <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the Ninth, <hi>Innocent</hi> the Fourth, <hi>Boniface</hi> the Second, <hi>Clement</hi> the Third, <hi>John</hi> the Twenty ſecond, <hi>Clement</hi> the Fourth, <hi>Benedict</hi> the Eleventh, <hi>Alexander</hi> the Fourth, and <hi>Martin</hi> the Fifth, have grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (amongſt them) forty years and nine Months of Indulgence. And <hi>John</hi> the Twenty Second hath granted an Indulgence to them of ten years and nine Monthes, and of twice forty days ſpace.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall hear the Maſs of one of the Order of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants newly made Prieſt, <hi>Clement</hi> the Fourth hath granted an Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of twice forty days ſpace; <hi>Innocent</hi> the Fourth of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred days; <hi>Gregory</hi> the Third of twice forty days ſpace; <hi>Honorio</hi> the Third of twice forty days ſpace; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the Fifth of two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred days; <hi>Boniface</hi> the Eighth of forty days; and <hi>Alexander</hi> the Fourth of an hundred days, the which make in all one year, eighty days, and eight times forty days ſpace</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſtand and hearken to the <hi>Salve Regina,</hi> or any other Laud that is ſaid before the Altar of the Servants of our Lady <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dromaco</hi> the Cardinal, (Entituted by St. <hi>Euſtachio</hi>) and Legate Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick of <hi>Italy,</hi> hath granted forty days Indulgence. And the like Indulgence is granted to thoſe that viſit the Altar of the Bleſſed Virgin in the Church of the Brothers of the Servants.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall any day viſit the Churches of the order of the Servants, <hi>Adrian</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Stephen</hi> the firſt, <hi>Sergio</hi> the third, <hi>John</hi> the tenth, <hi>John</hi> the eleventh, and <hi>Innocent</hi> the fourth, have each one granted them the Remiſſion of the third part of their ſins. And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152745:33"/>
                  <hi>Honorio</hi> the third hath given them twenty years and one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and eightie Daies of Indulgence. <hi>Clement</hi> the Third, ten years, and forty daies. <hi>Clement</hi> the fourth, thirty years, and forty daies. <hi>Boniface</hi> the eighth, twenty years, and forty daies. <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niface</hi> the ninth, two years. <hi>Alexander</hi> the fourth, twenty years, and an hundred and eighty daies. <hi>Lucio</hi> four years. <hi>Boniface</hi> the ſecond, thirty years, and an hundred and twenty daies. <hi>John</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, ten years, and eightie daies. <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth, twenty years, and an hundred and twenty daies. <hi>Alexander</hi> the fourth, eighteen years, and eighty daies. And <hi>Innocent</hi> the fourth hath given forty daies.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall ſay a <hi>Pater-Noſter</hi> and an <hi>Ave-Maria</hi> for the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and the dead, <hi>Innocent</hi> the fourth hath granted forty daies; <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth forty daies, <hi>Honorio</hi> the eighth, forty daies; <hi>Benedict</hi> the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leventh an hundred daies; <hi>Benedict</hi> the ſeventh an hundred daies; and <hi>Latino</hi> Cardinal, and Legate of <hi>Toſcana,</hi> forty daies indulgence.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall viſit the Churches of the order of the Servants in the Solemnitie of the Nativity, Circumciſion, Ephiphanie, and Aſcention of Chriſt, and upon <hi>Corpus Chriſti</hi> day, <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth hath granted an indulgence of an hundred years, and of an hundred times forty daies ſpace; <hi>Martin</hi> the fifth of forty years, and of ten times forty daies ſpace. <hi>John</hi> the twenty ſecond of forty years, and of twelve times forty daies ſpace. <hi>Nicholas</hi> the third of forty years, and the Remiſſion of the third part of their ſins. <hi>Clement</hi> the fourth of forth years; <hi>Siſto</hi> the fourth of forty years; and <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth of ſeven hundred years, and of ſeven hundred times forty daies ſpace.</p>
               <p>And moreover to thoſe that ſhall viſit the ſame in the Feaſt of the Aſcention, <hi>Inoncent</hi> the ninth hath granted an hundred years, and hundred times forty daies ſpace of indulgence <hi>Martin</hi> the fifth, forty years, and twelve times forty daies ſpace. <hi>Gregory</hi> the tenth, forty years. And <hi>Leo</hi> the fourth, ſeven years, and ten times forty daies ſpace. Alſo <hi>Adrian</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Stephen</hi> the fifth, <hi>Sergio</hi> the third, <hi>John</hi> the tenth, <hi>John</hi> the eleventh, <hi>Sergio</hi> the fifth, and <hi>Innocent</hi> the fourth, have each one granted a Remiſſion to them of the third part of their ſins; and this they have done not onely for the day of the Feaſt, but alſo daily during the Octave. The which do amount in all to two thouſand years, one hundred ſeventie four daies, nine hundred and fortie times forty daies ſpace, and ſeven times the Remiſſion of the third part of their ſins.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall viſit the Churches of the order of the Servants, in the Feſtivals of the bleſſed Virgin, to wit, the Aſſumption, Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, Conception, Viſitation, Preſentation, Purification, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152745:34"/>from the firſt Veſpers of each Feaſt, until after Sun Riſing the next morning; <hi>Siſto</hi> the fourth hath granted a plenary In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence. <hi>Honorio</hi> the eighth, forty years. <hi>Nicholas</hi> the fifth, eighty-years, and eightie times forty daies ſpace. <hi>Leo</hi> the fourth, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven years, and ſeven times forty daies ſpace. <hi>Boniface</hi> the fourth, forty years. <hi>Innocent</hi> the fourth, a thouſand years. <hi>Innocent</hi> the eighth three years, and an hundred times forty daies ſpace. <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth, eight hundred years, and eightie times forty daies ſpace. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> the fourth, forty ſix years and twelve daies. <hi>Martin</hi> the fifth, forty years and an hundred daies. <hi>John</hi> the twentie ſecond, forty years, and an hundred daies. <hi>Benedict</hi> the eleventh, ſeven years. <hi>Nicholas</hi> the third, three hundred and eightie daies. <hi>Innocent</hi> the fourth, forty years. <hi>Boniface</hi> the eighth, forty years. <hi>Nicholas</hi> the fourth, forty nine years, and forty daies. <hi>Gregory</hi> the eleventh, forty years, and forty daies. <hi>Gregory</hi> the tenth, forty years. <hi>Clement</hi> the fourth, ten years, and forty daies. <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth, twenty years and forty daies. And <hi>Alexander</hi> the fourth, twenty years, and 40 daies. Which do amount in all to one plenary indulgence, and one thouſand eight hundred eight years forty daies, and a thouſand and four times forty daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall viſit the Churches of the order of the Servants, in the Feaſts of the twelve Apoſtles, <hi>Benedict</hi> the eleventh hath grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſeven years Indulgence. <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth, an hundred years, and an hundred daies. <hi>Martin</hi> the fourth forty years, and forty daies. <hi>Gregory</hi> the eleventh forty years, and forty daies. And <hi>Innocent</hi> the eighth, three years, and an hundred times forty daies ſpace; which amount in all to a thouſand three hundred and eighty years, an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and forty daies, and an hundred times fortie daies ſpace.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that ſhall viſit the Churches belonging to the order of the Servants in the day of their Conſecration of the ſame; <hi>Clement</hi> the fifth hath granted ſeventeen years, and ſeventeen times forty daies ſpace of Indulgence. <hi>Benedict</hi> the eleventh, thirty ſeven years, and three times forty daies ſpace of Indulgence. <hi>Alexander</hi> the fifth, eight years, and twice forty daies ſpace. <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth, twenty years, and two daies. <hi>Nicholas</hi> the third, thirty years, and thirty times forty daies ſpace: and <hi>Clement</hi> the fourth, ten years, and ten times forty daies ſpace. Which make in the whole an hundred twenty two years, and ſixtie two times forty daies ſpace.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall viſit the Churches appertaining to the order of the Servants in all the <hi>Sundays</hi> of the year, <hi>Benedict</hi> the eleventh hath granted ſeven years Indulgence. And by <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> they
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152745:34"/>obtain the Indulgences which are at the holy Sepulchre, and at S. <hi>James</hi> of <hi>Galitia;</hi> and alſo an Indulgence of three thouſand years and of three thouſand times forty daies ſpace, granted by S. <hi>Silve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> Pope.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall viſit the Churches belonging to the order of the Brothers and Siſters of the Order of the Servants in the daies of <hi>Lent, Alexander</hi> the fourth, <hi>Nicholas</hi> the third, <hi>Innocent</hi> the fourth and <hi>Benedict</hi> the eleventh have granted, from <hi>Aſh Wedneſday</hi> until the end of the Reſurrection incluſively, any day, an hundred twenty two years, and five hundred ſeventy ſix daies; and to thoſe that upon <hi>Wedneſdays, Frydays,</hi> and <hi>Saturday,</hi> ſhall go and hear a Sermon, he hath joyned thereto, for any time they ſhall do thus, ſix years, and twenty ſix daies of Indulgence. And <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the fourth hath granted forty years Indulgence. And <hi>Innocent</hi> the eighth, beginning from <hi>Septuageſima Sunday,</hi> and ending at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> hath granted a thouſand years, and a thouſand times forty daies ſpace, and upon <hi>Wedneſday Thurſday,</hi> and <hi>Fryday,</hi> in the holy Week, a plenarie Indulgence. And <hi>Siſto</hi> the fourth, from the ſixth <hi>Feriae</hi> after the third <hi>Sunday,</hi> through the whole Octave of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> any day, hath granted an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence of three thouſand ſeven hundred and eighteen years and one hundred and thirtie daies. And <hi>Benedict</hi> the tenth hath granted any day eightie years, and eightie times forty daies ſpace, and twice the Remiſſion of the third part of their ſins; and by going to a Church dedicated to S. <hi>Salvatore,</hi> any day, they obtain a plenary Indulgence.</p>
               <p>To thoſe that ſhall viſit the Churches of the holy order of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in the Feaſts enſueing, have been granted by divers Popes theſe Indulgences following; to wit,</p>
               <p>The day of S. <hi>Anthony,</hi> by <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth, and <hi>Innocent</hi> the fourth, a thouſand years and an hundred daies Indulgence.</p>
               <p>The day of S. <hi>Fabian,</hi> and <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> by <hi>Leo</hi> the fourth, and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> the fourth, a thouſand years, and ſeven times forty daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
               <p>The day of S. <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Aquine,</hi> by <hi>John</hi> the twenty ſecond, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> the fifth, and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the fifth, an hundred and forty years.</p>
               <p>The day of S. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> by <hi>Innocent</hi> the Eighth, <hi>Martin</hi> the Fifth, and <hi>Leo</hi> the Fourth, a thouſand two hundred and forty ſeven years, and two hundred thirty two times fortie daies ſpace of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence. And by <hi>Siſto</hi> the Fourth the Remiſſion of the third part of their ſins.</p>
               <p>The day of S. <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, by <hi>Gregory</hi> the Ninth, <hi>Innocent</hi> the Eighth, <hi>Leo</hi> the Fourth, and <hi>Martin</hi> the Fifth, a thouſand two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152745:35"/>forty ſeven years, and two hundred thirty two times forty days ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
               <p>The day of S. <hi>Dominick,</hi> by <hi>Clement</hi> the Fourth, <hi>Gregory</hi> the Ninth, <hi>Boniface</hi> the Eighth, <hi>Nicholas</hi> the Fourth, <hi>Innocent</hi> the Fourth, <hi>Alexander</hi> the Fourth, <hi>Boniface</hi> the Second, <hi>John</hi> the Twenty Second, <hi>Alexander</hi> the Fifth, and <hi>Siſto</hi> the Fourth, ſeventy ſeven hundred thouſand years Indulgence.</p>
               <p>The day of S. <hi>Philip</hi> our Brother, by <hi>Martin</hi> the Fourth, and <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the Fourth, forty hundred years, and twelve times forty days ſpace.</p>
               <p>The day of the Apparition of S. <hi>Michael</hi> Arch-Angel by <hi>Leo</hi> the Fourth, ſeven years, and ſeven times forty daies ſpace, and by <hi>Nicholas</hi> the Fourth, the like Indulgence.</p>
               <p>The day of S. <hi>Francis,</hi> by <hi>Gregory</hi> the Ninth, and <hi>Martin</hi> the Fourth, an hundred and forty Years, and twelve times fortie daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
               <p>The day of all Saints, by <hi>Leo</hi> the Fourth, and <hi>Innocent</hi> the Fourth a thouſand and ſeven Years, and ſeven times fortie daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
               <p>The day of S. <hi>Nicholas,</hi> by <hi>Leo</hi> the Fourth, ſeven years, and ſeven times forty daies ſpace of Indulgence.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:152745:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATOR'S APPENDIX.</head>
            <head type="sub">Wherein the very Grounds and Foundations of the ſaid In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences are utterly overthrown, and conſequently the Indulgences themſelves apparently proved to be a meer Cheat.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Wherein is ſhewed what the Indulgences before mentioned are, and upon what they are grounded.</head>
               <p>THE ſaid Indulgences, according to the Doctrine of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, are certain Diſtributions made by the Pope, of certain penal and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory Works, taken by him out of the Churches Treaſury, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed to ſuch perſons, as although dying in the ſtate of grace, yet having not firſt here in this world fully ſatisfied the Juſtice of God for their ſins, are after their death caſt into Purgatory, where they are burnt and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in the fire thereof, until ſuch time the ſame be fully ſatisfied</p>
               <p>They are grounded upon certain falſe and pernicious Tenents, whereby ſhe hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; Firſt, that there lyeth a neceſſity upon all the Faithful (notwithſtanding their Redemption by Chriſt) to ſatisfie and content the Juſtice of God for their ſins; which ſatisfaction the Catechiſm of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> defineth thus:<note place="margin">Cap. de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramento Peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</note> 
                  <hi>Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio eſt rei debitae integra ſolutio: Eſt compenſatio, cum homo pro peccatis commiſſis Deo aliquid perſolvi.</hi> Satisfaction is an entire Payment of that thing which is due, and a recompence which a man maketh to God for his ſins. And it is made (they ſay) here in this life, by faſting, whipping, Pilgrimages, giving ſomething to the Church, and ſuch like works of Penance; and after this life, by being impriſoned, involved, and tormented in a fire called Purgatory.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That many in this life do not only ſatisfie the Divine Juſtice for their ſins, but exceed the ſame for them, in their ſatisfactions; for there be many, ſay they, that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152745:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>have ſinned but little, yet have ſatisfied very much; and conſequently have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone more Puniſhments than their ſins have deſerved, or Gods Juſtice for the ſame required; and this exceſs or ſuperfluity, which they call <hi>Superabundant Satisfaction:</hi> That is to ſay, the overplus that theſe men have paid to God, more than they need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have done, may be given to others that want the ſame.</p>
               <p>And, thirdly, That the Church hath a certain Treaſury, in which are reſerved ineſtimable Treaſures; that is to ſay, the ſaid ſuperabundant ſatisfactions; to wit, the ſuperabundant ſatisfactions of the Saints, Martyrs, Monks, Nuns, Fryers, Ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, and ſuch like others, as have ſatisfied beyond Gods Juſtice, or the deſert of their ſins: Of which Treaſury the Pope having the Keys, and being thereof Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian, turneth the ſaid Treaſures into pay for others, and bequeaths them out by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, to thoſe that are wanting in ſatisfactory Works.</p>
               <p>Theſe Indulgences, (although they are now, and have been of late years, (through the great reſort of Pilgrims to the places unto whom they are given, and the great and ſplendid Solemnities of the Jubilees at <hi>Rome</hi>) had in great venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and eſteem among the <hi>Romaniſts</hi>) were never known in the Churches Infancy, nor for a long time afterward,<note place="margin">Alph. congr. bareſ. <hi>8.</hi> verbe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgentia. Durand. Sontent. <hi>4.</hi> diſt. <hi>20.</hi> quae. <hi>3.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>den, Seſſ <hi>25.</hi> Decretum de Indulg.</note> but as <hi>Alphonſus à Caſtro</hi> confeſſeth, <hi>harum uſus in Eccleſia videtur ſtrò receptus,</hi> their uſe is ſeen to have been received but lately in the Church: and moreover <hi>Durand</hi> (another of their own Writers) telleth us, <hi>De Indulgentiis pauca dici poſſunt per certitudiuem; quia nec ſcriptura expreſsè de iis loquitur: Sancti etiam Ambroſius, Hilarius,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>minimè loquuntur de Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis.</hi> Little can be ſaid of any certainty of Indulgences, or of their being undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly true, ſeeing the Scriptures ſpeak not expreſly of them: and S. <hi>Hilary,</hi> S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> and other Fathers, ſpeak not at all of them. And yet the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> doth not only teach and command them to be retained in the Church, but alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth all them with a Curſe, which either term them unprofitable, or deny the Churches Authority to grant them.</p>
               <p>Now, what a bold preſumption was it for a Council to determine a new and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Doctrine for a Point of Faith? And what a ſenſeleſs and weak Faith muſt it needs be, which wanteth Antiquity, Authority of Scriptures, and conſent of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? But I will not ſtand to argue this, in regard it maketh not much to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purpoſe; neither will I altogether deny, but the ſaid Indulgences are to ſome profitable: For indeed (ſince many are come to have ſo good an opinion as they have of them) they are not only profitable, but very profitable to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. For, firſt, hereby ſhe eſtabliſheth, confirmeth, and upholdeth all her wicked, new-fangled, Idolatrous, and abſurd Doctrines, and doth eaſily impoſe them upon the Faith of thoſe, that perhaps otherwiſe might doubt of them; and the People are thereby (as it were) allured and enticed into a belief of that which before, it may be, they never heard of, or once thought of, nay peradventure not only doubted, but altogether diſliked of. And therefore when the Pope would eſtabliſh any new Opinion, or confirm it when called in queſtion, he preſently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triveth the doing thereof by ſome Indulgence that may conduce thereunto. As for Example, tending to the Adoration of Images, and Prayer to Saints departed, whoſoever (being in the ſtate of Grace) ſhall ſay ſeven Prayers before the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifix, and ſeven <hi>Pater-noſters,</hi> and ſeven <hi>Ave Maria's,</hi> ſhall obtain ſix and fifty thouſand years of Indulgence; to wit, fourteen thouſand granted by S. <hi>Gregory,</hi> fourteen thouſand by <hi>Nicholas</hi> the firſt, and twenty eight thouſand by <hi>Sixtus</hi> the Fourth.<note place="margin">Theſau. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg.</note> Tending to the Adoration of Saints Reliques, and other like things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to their Altars, to whoſoever, before an Altar, ſhall ſay <hi>Miſerere, Siſto</hi> the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:152745:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>Fourth hath granted all the Indulgences that are that day in <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Indulg.</note> Tending to Prayer for the dead, to whoſoever ſhall ſay the Office for the dead, <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth hath granted a Plenary Indulgence, and to ſuch as ſhall ſay one <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> and one <hi>Ave Maria</hi> for them, <hi>Innocent</hi> the Fourth hath granted forty days Indulgence: <hi>Gregory</hi> the Ninth, forty days: <hi>Honorius</hi> the Eighth, forty days: <hi>Benedict</hi> the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renth, an hundred days: and <hi>Lotino</hi> Cardinal, forty days: and in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner tending to all ſuch like Doctrines. Secondly, By the ſame ſhe maketh her ſelf fat, getteth good ſtore of Coyn, and accumulateth to her ſelf whole heaps of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, whereby ſhe is able to erect moſt ſumptuous Pallaces, build moſt famous Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries, manage and maintain Wars, and carry on all her wicked and ſelf-ended Deſigns.<note place="margin">Mod. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am. Sat. Ord Cand. de Indulg. In the Book called <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſio Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſien. cure pro Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate,</hi> pag. <hi>77.</hi>
                  </note> For you muſt know that theſe Indulgences (although the <hi>Romanists</hi> would fain have them to be heretofore called <hi>Donationes,</hi> to wit, Gifts: to the end that thereby, if it be poſſible, they may find out ſome way whereby to found them upon the Holy Scriptures,) do not at all, when they are bequeathed, come <hi>gratis,</hi> but muſt be well paid for: Inſomuch, that only the Indulgences, with the Letters of Pardon, and the <hi>Reſervationes, Pectorales, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>tales, Regreſſor, Gome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> and <hi>Speciales acceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> with other ſuch like Trifles, are adjudged to be worth to the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> in <hi>France</hi> only, above two hundred thouſand Crowns a year; and in all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> to be worth above ten Millions of Crowns yearly; which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is a pretty Sum.</p>
               <p>But that they are, in the leaſt, profitable to the perſons who are ſuppoſed to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them, and to whom they are granted as Indulgences, I deny utterly. <hi>For a Man can by no means redeem his Brother, or pay a Ranſom to God for him;</hi> (no not for the Body, and therefore much leſs for the Soul) <hi>for the Redemption of the Soules precious, and it ceaſeth for ever, Pſal.</hi> 49.7, 8. And the dead have not any more Reward, <hi>neither have they any more Portion for ever, in any thing that is done under the Sun,</hi> Eccleſ. 9.5, 6.</p>
               <p>Theſe and the like Teſtimonies are ſo plain and manifeſt againſt the validity of the ſaid Indulgences, that ſeveral of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> (by the Relation of <hi>Thomas Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi>) have been of Opinion, (as <hi>Greg. de valent.</hi> affirmeth,<note place="margin">The Aqu. in ſuppl. <hi>3.</hi> Part. <hi>4.</hi> Qu. <hi>25.</hi> Art. <hi>5.</hi> Greg. de val. de In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg. Cap. <hi>2</hi>
                  </note>) That <hi>Eccleſiaſtical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence</hi> of it ſelf could remit no Puniſhment, <hi>Nec in fore Eccleſiae, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in fore Dei;</hi> neither in the judgment of the Church, nor in the judgment of God; but that it was a pious kind of Fraud, whereby the Church by promiſing ſuch Remiſſion might allure men to the devout performance of thoſe pious works which were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the Form of the Indulgence; even as when a Mother to move her Child to run doth Promiſe him an Apple, yet notwithſtanding afterward ſhe doth not give it him.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee that divers of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> themſelves (as 'tis here acknowledged) have held Indulgences to be given only to allure and intice men to a devout Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of what is required in the Form of the Indulgence: (which is according to what I have here before ſhewed; and that they are not at all profitable as Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, but are in themſelves meer cheats.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs this is not all, they are not only meer cheats, and altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable as Indulgences, but alſo Damnable; and the Perſons are accurſed that broach and maintain them: For although they concern Chriſt and his Church, and appertain (as the Papiſts tell us) to our Faith and Life, yet they are not received in the Legal and Evangelical Scriptures.</p>
               <p>That they are not received in the Legal and Evangelical Scriptures, is a truth ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that it is even confeſſed and acknowledged by the Romaniſts themſelves;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:152745:37"/>for beſides <hi>Duranaus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Anto. Part. <hi>1.</hi> Tit. <hi>10</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> Prier. Contr. Luth pro Indulg.</note> of whom I have before ſpoken, <hi>Antenint</hi> ſaith, <hi>De Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiis nil expreſſe habemns in Sacra Scriptura, &amp;c.</hi> Concerning Indulgences we have nothing expreſly in the Holy Scriptures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Silveſter Pierias</hi> ſaith, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgentiae Authoritate Scripturae non innotuere nobis, ſed Authoritate Eccleſiae Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, &amp; Romanerum Pontificum, quae major eſt Authoritas.</hi> Indulgences are not known to us by the Authority of the Scripture, but by the Authority of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church, and of the <hi>Roman Popes,</hi> which is greater than the Authority of the Scripture.</p>
               <p>And that they are therefore damnable, and the perſons are accurſed that broach and maintain them,<note place="margin">Aug. Contr. lit. Petil. l. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi> Tom. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> is alſo manifeſt; for S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Sive de Chriſto, ſive de Eccleſia, ſibe de quatanque alia re, que pertinet ad fidem vitamque noſtram, non dream nos, nequaquam comparandi ei qui dixit, ſed ſi Angelus de caelo vobis annun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciaverit praeterquam quod in Scripturis Legalibus &amp; Evangelicis accepiſtis, Anathema ſit.</hi> Whether concerning Chriſt, or his Church, or any other thing appertaining to our Faith and Life, I will not ſay if we (who are no way to be compared to him that ſo ſpare) but if an Angel from Heaven ſhall preach unto you any thing but what you have received in the Legal and Evangelical Scriptures, let him be accurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And S. <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Edit. Baſil. pa. <hi>437.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. all that which is without the Scripture, Divinely inſpired, not being of Faith, is ſin; for (ſaith he) Faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the word of God, and all that is not of Faith is Sin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Wherein is ſhewed, That Chriſt hath fully and perfectly made ſatisfaction to God for our ſins, and that the Doctrine of our ſatisfaction over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth our Faith and Devotion, and is manifeſtly falſe, is injurious to Chriſt, blaſphemous againſt God, teacheth men to be diſloyal and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeful, implyeth an impoſſibility, and is alſo needleſs.</head>
               <p>I <hi>Renaeus,</hi> writing againſt <hi>Valentinus,</hi> and other like <hi>Hereticks,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Scripturis Divinis uiti, quae certa &amp; indubitata veritas eſt, in firma &amp; valida Petra eſt Domum ſuam aedificare; hac vero derelista aliis niti quibuſdam Doctrinis effuſa are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae (unde facilis everſio) eſt Domum ſuam adificare.</hi> To lean upon the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which are the ſure and undoubted truth, is for a man to build his houſe upon a ſure and ſtrong Rock; but if leaving it (that is, the truth of the Scriptures) he ſticketh to ſome other Doctrine, the ſame is to build his houſe upon the unſtedfaſt Sand, from whence it is eaſily overthrown.</p>
               <p>Now that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath fully and perfectly ſatisfied God for our ſins, and hath wholly and only wrought our Redemption, Purgation, and Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, is a Doctrine grounded upon the holy Scriptures, for the holy Scriptures at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute the ſame wholly and only to him, affirming, <hi>that Jeſus Christ hath waſhed us from our ſins in his own blood,</hi> Rev. 1.5. <hi>That he his own ſelf bare our ſins in his own Body on the Tree, by whoſe stripes we are healed,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.24. <hi>That through him we have peace with God,</hi> Rom. 5.1. <hi>That he is the Reconciliation for our ſins, and not
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152745:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>for ours only, but alſo for the ſins of the whole world,</hi> 1 Joh. 2.2. <hi>That be was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, bruiſed for our iniquities, had the chaſtiſement of our Peace laid upon him, and with his ſtripes we are healed,</hi> Iſa. 53.5. <hi>That he hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained eternal redemption for us,</hi> Heb. 9.12. <hi>That by one Offering he hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified,</hi> Heb. 10.14. <hi>That he it able to ſave them to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt that come to God by him,</hi> Heb. 7.25. <hi>That it pleaſed the Father by him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile all things to himſelf, both which are in Earth, and which are in Heaven,</hi> Col. 1.19, 20. <hi>That there is no Salvation in any other, nor other Name under Heaven where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we muſt be ſaved,</hi> Act. 4.12. And to be ſhort, it is the whole ſcope of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>And yet the Papiſts (neither regarding Scripture, Goſpel, <hi>Irenous,</hi> nor any other thing that may make againſt their pretended ſatisfactions) will have a neceſſity lye upon us to pay and ſatisfie God for our ſins.</p>
               <p>But this their Doctrine, firſt, overthroweth our Faith, deſtroyeth our Devotion, and is manifeſtly falſe; for we are taught to <hi>believe the forgiveneſs of our ſins, and to pray for the forgiveneſs of our ſins, and God forgiveth us our ſins,</hi> and that free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: whereas God could not be ſaid to forgive us our ſins, did he either here in this life, or hereafter in the other, require ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>Secondly, It is injurious to Chriſt, for it defaceth the ſufficiency of his Death.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, It is blaſphemous againſt God; for firſt, it maketh him like a very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt and hard Landlord, who having granted an Eſtate in a Bargain to a younger Brother, upon a ſufficient Fine tendred by the Elder, yet will not let the younger enjoy it, unleſs he Fine for it again himſelf.</p>
               <p>Secondly, It maketh him like a cruel Creditor, who having the Debt diſcharged to the uttermoſt, by a Friend, yet caſteth the poor Debtor himſelf into Priſon, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til he there alſo in part make ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, It maketh him like a mercileſs Judge, who having puniſhed an effence with condign puniſhment, yet will have the Offender puniſhed again, as if he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in the torments of the miſerable.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, It maketh men diſloyal and revengeful, and miniſtreth matter to mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious perſons, to the fully ſatisfying their malicious humours, ſeeing as God doth pardon us, ſo we ought to deal with others; and therefore if God doth ſo forgive us our ſins in Chriſt, as that we muſt ſtill either here afflict our ſelves with the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous works of Penance, or elſe hereafter be caſt into the extreme torments of Purgatory; then we may alſo ſo forgive our Brother, as that we may yet procure his moſt grievous puniſhment; and ſay, 'tis true, I have pardoned him, but I will not yet ceaſe extremely to puniſh him; for will you have me to be more patient and merciful than God himſelf, that dealeth thus with us? who after having declared that all our faults are forgiven, either ceaſeth not here to torment us by our Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Whipping, Pilgrimaging, and ſuch like Penal Works, or hereafter to burn us for I know not how many thouſand years in a ſcorching Fire.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, It implieth an impoſſibility, for ſatisfactions for ſins ought to be accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the quality of the Perſon thereby offended, and God and the Divine Juſtice being altogether Infinite, require therefore an infinite ſatisfaction, which no ſinite Creature can poſſibly make. But ſuppoſe there were a poſſibility of our making a recompence to God, and ſatisfying the Divine Juſtice for them, which there is not, yet.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, It is altogether needleſs, for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt by one offering hath perfected for ver them that are ſanctified,</hi> Heb. 10.14. And what Eſtate is there beyond that of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152745:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>Perfection? And what Perfection greater than that which abideth and continueth for ever?</p>
               <p>Now the <hi>Papiſts</hi> (to avoid thoſe groſs abſurdities and horrid conſequences, which otherwiſe they ſee muſt of neceſſity attend this their Doctrine) firſt will have that in ſin are two things; <hi>Malum Culpae, &amp; Poenam Culpae,</hi> the fault, and the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the fault, they ſay, is taken away, and ſatisfied for by Jeſus Chriſt; but the puniſhment is left behind, and is to be ſatisfied for by us. (Thus to take away the ſufficiency of Chriſts ſatisfaction, to the end they may imply a neceſſity of ours, they make up ſin into a certain Hodg-podge, containing both the fault, and the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as if the ſin were not the fault only; whereas the puniſhment is not in the leaſt any part of ſin, but the reward of ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23.) But this <hi>Fetch</hi> being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together defective, is eaſily defeated, and will not in the leaſt ſerve their turn. For the cauſe which only produceth an effect being taken away, by neceſſity the effect ceaſeth. Now the fault is the cauſe which only produceth ſatisfying puniſhment; therefore the fault being taken away, neceſſarily ſatisfying puniſhment is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. This is affirmed by <hi>Tertullian; Exempto</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>reatu, remittitur &amp; Paena,</hi> the fault being taken away, the puniſhment is omitted: And the ſame alſo is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted by our Saviour Chriſt, who no ſooner had forgiven the ſick of the Palſie his ſins, but his Palſie left him, <hi>Mar.</hi> 2. The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> alſo ſpeaking of Chriſt in the work of our Redemption, ſaith, <hi>He hath born our griefs, and carried our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows,</hi> Eſa. 53.4. which are not the guilt, but the puniſhment of our ſins. And S. <hi>Auguſtius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Suſcipiendo Chriſtus Poenam, &amp; non ſuſcipiendo culpam, &amp; cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pam delevit &amp; Poenam.</hi> Chriſt taking upon him the puniſhment, and not the fault, hath aboliſhed both the fault and puniſhment.</p>
               <p>When they ſee therefore that this faileth them, and that Chriſt hath ſatisfied not only for the fault, but the puniſhment of ſin, then they begin to inſiſt upon the kinds of puniſhment: And ſecondly will have, that Chriſt hath ſatisfied for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal puniſhment, but not for the Temporal. As for the Temporal puniſhment, they ſay it remaineth, and is to be ſatisfied for by us (as if the Temporal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were not contained in the Eternal, or that God through Chriſt ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give us an Eternal puniſhment, but not a Temporal:) But this alſo is a meer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, is altogether as defective as the former, and will not ſtand them in any ſtead at all: For S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>There is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Joſus,</hi> Rom. 8.1. and if none, then neither Eternal nor Temporal. God himſelf ſaith of his People, <hi>I will forgive their iniquity, and I will remember their ſin no more,</hi> Jer. 31.34. And if God forgiveth our iniquity, and in ſuch ſort as that he will remember our ſin no more, it followeth that he will not be ſatisfied for the ſame with temporal puniſhment. God is ſaid alſo freely to forgive us our Treſpaſſes, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.13. and if freely, then without requiring in the leaſt our ſatisfaction. Moreover, he is ſaid to forgive us all our Debt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.32. and if all our Debt, then not only the ſin, but alſo the puniſhment; and not only the Eternal puniſhment, but alſo the Temporal: And S. <hi>Paul</hi> again alſo (ſpeaking of Chriſt ſaith, <hi>It plenſed the Father that in him ſhould all Fulneſs dwell,</hi> Col. 1.19. and if all Fulneſs, then Fulneſs of ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>When they ſee therefore that this Wile alſo faileth them, and that Chriſt hath ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfied for our ſins, then they begin to inſiſt upon the tim of the ſins being committed; and thirdly, they will have that Chriſt hath fully ſatisfied for ſins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted before Baptiſm, but not for ſins committed after Baptiſm. As for ſins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted after Baptiſm, they ſay they are left to us, and we ought to ſatisfie, pay, and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:152745:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>make recompence to God for them (as if that God would be more favourable to thoſe that ſin before Baptiſm, than to thoſe that ſin after Baptiſm; eſpecially when the one oftentimes ſin through malice, and the other through infirmity.) But this Wile alſo is altogether deficient, and ſerveth to help them no more than the others before-mentioned: For S. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Blood of Jeſus Chriſt cleanſeth us from all ſin,</hi> 1 Joh. 1.7. and if from all ſin, then as well from ſin committed after Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, as ſin committed before Baptiſm: And S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>That by Jeſus Chriſt God pardoneth all our offences,</hi> Col. 2.13. and if God by Chriſt forgiveth all our offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, then again as well thoſe committed after, as before Baptiſm.</p>
               <p>When they ſee that all thoſe Wiles and Subtilties fail them, and that none will procure them ſo much as room for our ſatisfactions, (rather than their Church ſhould be put to a <hi>Non-plus</hi>) ſome will have that Chriſts ſatisfactions ſerve only to make ours available: (as if Chriſt died to make our ſufferings of worth before God, and to the end we might ſuffer a Divine Vengeance.) But this helpeth them not at all, and is manifeſtly falſe; for Chriſt died not to make our ſufferings of any worth before God, but to free and exempt us from ſuffering.</p>
               <p>The benefit of his Paſſion conſiſted not in enabling of us to pay, but in paying and ſatisfying to God for us. He gave us not the vertue to pay our own Ranſome, but (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) <hi>He gave himſelf a Ranſome for us,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.6. And <hi>the Son of God hath by himſelf purged our ſins,</hi> Heb. 1.3. and if by himſelf, then not at all by our ſatisfactions.</p>
               <p>Others (perceiving it is in vain to imply a neceſſity of ours, by leſſening of Chriſts Satisfactions) will have the remiſſion of ſins to be altogether a peculiar be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of Chriſts Paſſion; but withall, that the ſame ought to be applied to us by our ſatisfactions; (as if forgiveneſs were to be applied by payment, and pardon by puniſhment:) But this will not help them neither; for our Penal Works are not the means whereby to apply to us the benefits of Chriſts Paſſion. The benefits of Chriſts Paſſion are not apply'd to us by a Monks <hi>Coul,</hi> or a Hair Shirt, or the yerks of a Whip, or the Fire of Purgatory, or by going on Pilgrimage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe are but weak and beggerly Elements, and yokes of Bondage, from which God hath ſent his Son to redeem us, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.3, 4. Chriſt hath freed us, and the Scriptures have warned and admoniſhed us, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1. but the benefits of Chriſts Paſſion are applied to us by Faith in Chriſt: For the end of our Redemption was, that we might receive the Adoption of Sons, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.5. for being Sons, we are Heirs of God through Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.7. And <hi>we are the Sons of God by Faith in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Gal. 3.26.</p>
               <p>Others (again) bring in certain places of holy Scripture, whereby to prove their pretended ſatisfactions; <hi>viz.</hi> firſt they produce the puniſhments of the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> Chap. 12. ver 13. Chap. 13. ver. 28. Chap. 16. ver. 22. and how that God inflicted the ſame upon him for certain ſins, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.10, 11, 14. which before were forgiven him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.13 But this maketh nothing for their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; for the Queſtion is of Satisfactory Puniſhments: whereas thoſe inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Prophet <hi>David</hi> were only Caſtigatory.</p>
               <p>There is a great diſterence betwixt puniſhments Satisfactory, and puniſhments Caſtigatory; for the one (as they ſay) are brought to pay and make recompence to God, and ſatisfie his Divine Juſtice, but the other are brought to correct and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the ſinner, to humble and exerciſe him, leſt he fall any more into the like ſin, and to keep others from the like offences. Now that theſe of the Prophet <hi>David</hi> were ſuch, is affirmed by S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who (ſpeaking of thoſe, and other like puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152745:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the godly) ſaith; <hi>Non manent ut Plagae peccatis, ſed ut exercitationes pio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum;</hi> they remain not as puniſhments for ſins, but as exerciſes of juſt men.</p>
               <p>Secondly, They alledge the counſel given by <hi>Daniel</hi> to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> to wit, <hi>Redeem thy ſins by Alms, and thy iniquities by ſhewing mercy to the poor,</hi> Dan. 4.27. But this ſerveth not their turn neither: For <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaketh here of redeeming and ſatisfying before men, (exhorting the King to recompence by liberality all ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as he had any way wronged or injured) and not of redeeming, in reſpect of God; beſides, Alms are good works, and not puniſhments, or Penances: And which is more, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> would have that Alms and other ſatisfactions ſerve not to ſatisfie for ſins, but for the puniſhments due to ſins. Moreover, this King was a <hi>Pagan</hi> uncircumciſed, and therefore (according to the Doctrine of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi>) not only liable to eternal puniſhments, whereas they would have ſatisfactions to be only for Temporol, but his ſatisfactions were of no worth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Wherein is ſhewed, that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> Doctrine of <hi>Purgatory</hi> overthroweth the Faith of the Goſpel, is againſt the Authority of Chriſt, deſtroyeth the Teſtimony of the Fathers, condemneth the Practice of all Chriſtian Churches, robbeth God of his Juſtice, maketh him a Mocker, and is contradicted by the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> own Tenents.</head>
               <p>BIſhop <hi>Fiſher</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ex Purgatorio p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>det omnis Indulgentiatum eſtimatio;</hi> The whole price of Indulgences hangeth on Purgatory. Purgatory again hangeth altogether upon the neceſſity pretended to lye upon the faithful, of their fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying (through their payment to God) the Divine Juſtice for their ſins.</p>
               <p>As for the neceſſity lying upon the faithful, of their ſatisfying (through pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to God) the Divine Juſtice for their ſins, the ſame is overthrown already, and by conſequence alſo Purgatory; nevertheleſs I have not ſaid (for the doing thereof) ſo much againſt the Doctrine of the one, but as much may be ſaid alſo againſt that of the other; for that the faithful go after this life into a place of fire and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and there remain till they are purged with ſatisfactory puniſhments, which is the Papiſts Doctrine of Purgatory; firſt overthroweth the Faith of the Goſpel. It is heavy news, not glad tidings, that they which believe in Chriſt, ſhall beſides their manifold croſſes and puniſhments in this life, go afterward to a place of far greater grief and ſorrow. The glad tidings of our Saviour Chriſt are quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, who ſaith, <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay unto you, he that heareth my words, and believeth in him that ſent me, hath everlaſting life, and ſhall not come into condemnation, but hath paſſed from death to life,</hi> Joh. 5.24. And yet none can deny, but this is the Faith of the Goſpel, this is the glad tidings to all true Chriſtians and Believers in Chriſt; and the ſame is confirmed by a double Oath, that they which hear his Word, and believe in God his Father, have everlaſting life; that is, are as ſure of it, as if they had it already, and ſhall not come into condemnation, either of temporal puniſhment after this life, or of eternal, but have paſſed from death to life; that is, from hence, to joy and felicity.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:152745:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Moreover, the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſaith unto God, <hi>If thou Lord wilt be extreme to mark what is done a miſs, who is able to abide it?</hi> Pſal. 130.3. intimating to us, that God will not call his to a ſtrict account. Chriſt will not be aſhamed of thoſe that are his, before God and the holy Angels, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.16. <hi>There ſhall be no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Rom. 8.1.</p>
               <p>Almighty God having compleated in ſix days the Creation of the World, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day reſted from all his Works; even ſo, Chriſt having wrought our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, all that do here truly believe in him, and are careful to perform good works, at their departure hence, ſhall enter into reſt. They ſhall not need to fear Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; but as God reſted from all his labours, ſo they ſhall reſt from all their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. This was declared to S. <hi>John</hi> from Heaven; <hi>I heard a voice</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>from Heaven, ſaying unto me, write, bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord; from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, even ſo ſaith the Spirit, for they rest from their labours, and their works follow them,</hi> Rev. 14.13.</p>
               <p>The like is teſtified by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> who ſpeaking of the death of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, ſaith, <hi>The righteous is taken away from the evil to come; he ſhall enter into pence, they ſhall reſt in their Beds, each one walking in his uprightneſs,</hi> Eſa 57.1.2.</p>
               <p>Poor <hi>Lazaries</hi> was no ſooner departed this life, but was carried by Angels into <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi>'s boſom, where he was comforted and refreſhed, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.22. Jeſus Chriſt ſaid to the good Thief at his death, <hi>This day thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe,</hi> Luk. 23.43. And good old <hi>Simeon</hi> made no account but to enter into reſt after his death, ſaying, <hi>Lord, now let teſt thou thy ſervant depart in peace,</hi> Luk. 2.26.29.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith. <hi>If God be with us, who can be againſt us? He that ſpared not his own Son, but delivered him up for us all, how ſhall he not alſo with him freely give us all things?</hi> Rom. 8.31, 32. Here is the Riches of all good Chriſtians, God ſo loved them, that he gave them his Son; how much more will he not give them all things elſe? But they are ſinners, they are unprofitable ſervants, they are Prodigal Children, this will turn away Gods favour from them: but againſt this heavy news here is comfort, who will lay any thing to the charge of Gods Choſen? <hi>It is God that juſtifieth, who ſhall condemn? it is Chriſt which is dead, yea or rather which is riſen again, who is alſo at the right hand of God, and maketh requeſt for us.</hi> Rom. 8.33, 34. Though we often diſpleaſe God, even daily, yet we know Chriſt is his beloved Son, in whom the Father is well pleaſed, and for whoſe ſake we are accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And thoſe whom he accounteth his, 'tis in vain for Satan to ſtrive againſt; for they appear before God clad in the righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Since this therefore is the glad tidings of the Goſpel, (to wit, <hi>That he that heareth the word of Chriſt, and believeth in him that ſent him, hath everlaſting life, and ſhall not come into condemnation, but hath paſſed from death to life;</hi> and is confirmed alſo by all the aforeſaid Teſtimonies) let the Deaf Papiſts, and all Counterfeit Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, which will neither hear his Word, nor think they are bound to know and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it; take heed, leſt by this their obſtinacy and ſtopping their ears, to go, not into Purgatory, but into Hell; for S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith (and no doubt he ſaid it not in vain, but it ſhall have its force in ſome, and therefore mark it well) <hi>The Lord Jeſus ſhall come himſelf from Heaven, with his mighty Angels, in flaming fire, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering vengeance to them that know not God, and obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ,</hi> 1 Theſ. 1.8. And how can they obey the Goſpel, when they know it not, and refuſe to hear it? neither ſhall their Ignorance, the blind Mother of their Devotion, excuſe them, for Chriſt ſhall render vengeance to them that know not God.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:152745:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Secondly, The Doctrine of Purgatory is againſt the Authority of Chriſt; for he ſaith, <hi>Father, I will that they which thou bast given me be with me, even where I am, that they may behold my glory which thou haſt given me; for thou lovedſt me before the foundation of the World</hi> Joh. 17.24. This is Chriſts Will: And what Pope, what Devil can withſtand it? and he excepteth none. All his ſhall be with him; all good Chriſtians, as well great as ſmall; all his Members, as well weak as ſtrong, he will not ſuffer the leaſt of them to endure a moment the Fire of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory: And when this ſhall be, that they ſhall be with him, S. <hi>Paul</hi> plainly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth, at the hour of their deaths; and therefore (no doubt) upon the Goſpel grounding his Faith, he ſaith, <hi>I deſire to be looſed, and to be with Chriſt.</hi> This was the cauſe he deſired to be looſed out of the bonds of this ſinful fleſh, that he might be with Chriſt, as our Saviour here hath promiſed; and not to him only, but to all that his Father hath given him, to all his. And in another place, S. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſpeaking of all true Chriſtians, ſaith, <hi>We know that if our Earthly Houſe of this Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle were diſſolved, we have a building of God, a Houſe not made with hands, eternal in the Heavens,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.1. So that all the faithful have but two houſes or dwellings, the one Earthly, the other Heavenly; they have none at all in Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And he addeth further, <hi>God hath given us the earnest of his Spirit; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we always are of good courage, knowing this, that being at home in the body, we are abſent from the Lord (for we walk by Faith, not by Sight,) yet we are of good courage, and we deſire rather to go out of the body, and to be at home with the Lord,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.5, 6, 7, 8. Behold here are but two Eſtates of the faithful, of thoſe that are Jeſus Chriſts, that have received the earneſt of his Spirit, either to be at home here in the body, and to be Strangers with the Lord, to walk by faith, not by ſight; or elſe to go out of the body, and to ſee his glorious Majeſty, there ſhall be no mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle place to ſtay them in the way. And here this their aſſurance, this their good courage, and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is twice repeated; they fear not the performance of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, they fear no Purgatory, no torment in the way: let their Adverſary, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, do what he can againſt them in this life, hereafter they are ſure he cannot hurt them: <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>John</hi> (ſpeaking of this life) <hi>the Devil ſhall caſt ſome of you into priſon, that ye may be tryed, and ye ſhall have tribulation ten days: Be thou faithful unto death, and I will give thee a Crown of Life,</hi> Rev. 2.10.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The Doctrine of Purgatory deſtroveth the Teſtimony of the Fathers; for the Fathers (both <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi>) teſtifie the quite and clean contrary: <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory Nazianzen</hi> ſaith; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. I believe the words and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the wiſe, that is, that every good ſoul fearing God, being delivered from the body (which here it hath on Earth) and ſeparated from it, is preſently admitted to the enjoyment and contemplation of the good which is reſerved for it, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth admirable pleaſures. <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> in the 75. Queſtion of the Book of Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions and Anſwers to the Orthodox, at the end of his works ſaith, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. After the ſoul is departed out of the body, preſently a ſeparation is made of the good from the bad, for they are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by Angels to the places fit for them; the ſouls of the good into Paradiſe, where the Angels reſort, and are converſant, but the ſouls of the wicked into hell. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:152745:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>in his fourth Homily upon the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> ſpeaking of Hymns and Prayers that in his time were uſed at the Burials of the Dead, ſaith; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. What ſignifie theſe burning Tapers, but that we bury the Champions of Chriſt? and theſe Hymns, but that we glorifie God, and give him thanks, becauſe he hath crowned the Dead, and delivered him from all pain and grief. And in his ſecond Homily upon <hi>Lazarus,</hi> he ſaith; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. While we are here on Earth, we have fair hopes, but as ſoon as we have left this world, it is no more in our power to do Penance, or to undo or amend that which we have committed and done upon Earth. And the ſame is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> in his ſecond Book of Hereſies, in the 39. Hereſie, which is the Hereſie of the <hi>Novatians;</hi> and moreover he there addeth, that when the Soul hath left the body, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The Barns are ſhut up, the time is accompliſhed, the Combat is ended, the place of Liſts is empty, and the Crowns are given. S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his Book of the benefit of Death, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the day of Death, ſaith; <hi>Cùm dies advenerit, intrepide ad</hi> Abraham <hi>Patrem noſtrum proficiſcamur, intrepide pergamus ad illum caetum juſtorumque conventum, ibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus enim ad Patres noſtros, ibimus ad illos noſtrae fidei praeceptores, ut etiamſi opera de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſint, fides opituletur, defendatur hareditas.</hi> When that day cometh, we go aſſuredly to our Father <hi>Abraham,</hi> to the Aſſembly and company of the Juſt: For we ſhall go to our Fathers, we ſhall go to the Teachers of our Faith, to the end, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though our works fail us, our Faith may ſecure us, and the Inheritance be kept for us. And again, in the ſame Book, <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. he ſaith: <hi>Inſipientes mortem quaſi ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum malum, Supientes quaſi requiem poſt labores, &amp; finem malorum expetunt:</hi> Fools fear Death as the chiefeſt evil, but wiſe men deſire it, as a reſt after their Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, and the end of their evils. S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> in his firſt Treatiſe againſt <hi>Demetrian,</hi> ſaith; <hi>Aevi temporalis fine completo, ad aeterna vel mortis vel immortalitatis hoſpitia dividimur:</hi> This temporal life being ended, we are ſequeſtred into the habitation ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of eternal death, or eternal life. And towards the end of the ſame Treatiſe, he ſaith; <hi>Quando iſtinc exceſſum fuerit, nullus jam locus paenitentiae eſt, nullus ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factionis effectus. Hic vita aut amittitur aut tenetur, hic ſaluti aeternae cultu Dei, &amp; fructu fidei providetur:</hi> When we are gone from hence, there is no more place of Penance, no effect of ſatisfaction, life is here either loſt or won; Everlaſting Life (by the worſhip of God, and the fruits of Faith) is here provided for: And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over in his Book of Mortality, he ſaith; <hi>Deus tibi de hoc munde recedenti, immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem pollicetur atque aeternitatem, &amp; tu dubitas? hoc eſt Deum omnino non noſſe:</hi> God at thy going out of this world, promiſeth thee immortality and eternal life, and doeſt thou doubt hereof? this is not to know God at all as thou ſhouldſt. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his 54. Epiſtle to <hi>Macedonius,</hi> ſaith; <hi>Morum porro corrigendorum nullus alius quam in hac vita locus, nam poſt hanc vitam quiſque id habebit, quod in hac ſibimet conquiſierit:</hi> There is no other place to correct our manners and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but only in this life; for after this life every man ſhall have that which he hath purchaſed to himſelf here in this world. In his 13th Book of the City of God, <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. he ſaith; <hi>In requie ſunt animae piorum à corporibus ſeparata: impiorum au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem paenas luunt, donec iſtarum ad aeternam vitam, illarum vero ad aeternam mortem quae ſecunda dicitur, corpora reviviſcant:</hi> The ſoule of the godly being ſeparated
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152745:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>from their bodies, are in reſt; but the ſouls of the ungodly ſuffer puniſhment, until the bodies of them do riſe again unto everlaſting life, and the bodies of theſe to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal death, which is called the ſecond death. In his Book of the Vanity of the World, <hi>Tom.</hi> 9. <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. he ſaith; <hi>Scitote quod cum anima à corpore evellitur, aut in Paradiſo pro meritis bonis collocatur, aut certe pro peccatis in inferni tartara praecipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur:</hi> Know, that when the ſoul departeth out of the body, it is preſently placed in Paradiſe, becauſe of her good works, or is thrown down head-long into the Pit of Hell, becauſe of her ſins. And in the ſecond Sermon of the Conſolation of the Dead, which is in the ninth Tome of his works, he ſaith; <hi>Recedens anima ab An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelis ſuſcipitur &amp; collocatur aut-in ſinu</hi> Abrahae, <hi>ſi fidelis est, aut in carceris inferni cuſtodia, ſi peccatrix eſt:</hi> The ſoul going out of the body, is received and placed in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Boſom, if it be faithful; or in the Infernal Priſon of Hell, if it be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. And moreover in his 232. Sermon againſt Drunkenneſs, he ſaith; <hi>Nemo ſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiat, Fratres, duo enim loca ſunt, &amp; tertius non eſt ullus: Qui cumt Chriſto regnare non meruerit, cum Diabolo abſque dubitutione ulla Peribit:</hi> Let no man deceive himſelf, my Brethren, there are but two places, and a third there is not any: He that ſhall not merit to reign with Chriſt ſhall without doubt periſh with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. S. <hi>Hierome</hi> upon the ninth of the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> ſaith; <hi>Quando anima vincu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis larata-corporit, volandi quò velit ſive quò ire compellitur propter tenuitatem ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiae habuerit libertatem, aut ad inferna Ducetur, aut certe ad Coelestia ſubleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur:</hi> When the ſoul looſed from the bonds of the body ſhall be at liberty, becauſe of the lightneſs of its ſubſtance, to fly whither it will, or whither it is conſtrained to go, it ſhall either be carried to Hell, or without fail be lifted up to Heaven. And <hi>Gregory Nyſſen</hi> in the Book of thoſe that ſleep, ſaith; <hi>Per mortem ſoluto Bello quod in nobis eſt, pacem mens agitat:</hi> The War that is in us being ended by death, our ſouls reſt.</p>
               <p>Yea, the Fathers were ſo far from believing that faithful ſouls are tormented in fire until the-Reſurrection, (as the Papiſts would make men believe) that very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them held, that the ſoul ſeparated from the body could not ſuffer any tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in his 39. Homily upon the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthiane</hi> ſaith; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Although the ſoul remaineth, although it were ten thouſand times im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, as in truth it is, it ſhall not without the body receive thoſe unſpeakable bleſſings, nor ſuffer any puniſhment. <hi>Gregory Niſſen</hi> in his third Oration upon the Reſurrection of Chriſt, ſaith; <hi>Animam per ſe ſeparatim ignis nunquam attigerit, nec tenebrae quidem ei moleſtae fuerint, utpote quae oculis caret, &amp;c.</hi> Fire can never touch the ſoul ſeparated from the body, neither can darkneſs be troubleſome to it, becauſe it wanteth eyes, <hi>&amp;c. Tertullian</hi> in his Apology, <hi>Chap.</hi> 48. ſaith; <hi>Neque pati quicquam poteſt anima ſola ſine ſtabili materia, id eſt, Carne:</hi> The ſoul alone cannot ſuffer any thing without ſolid matter, that is, the Fleſh: Another affirmeth, that it is injuſtice to puniſh the ſoul for ſin before the Reſurrection, in regard the body hath been partaker with her; but he will have the body and ſoul, as they have ſinned both together, to be puniſhed both together; ſaying, <hi>If ſins ſhall be puniſhed before the Reſurrection, God ſhall not deal juſtly with the ſoul, for ſhe alone would be put to ſuffer the puniſhment of thoſe things which ſhe offended in the life, at the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbation of the body, drawing her to theſe appetites and motions.</hi> And according to S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> (in his tenth Chapter of the Book of the benefit of death) all the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment that ſouls ſuffer, being ſeparated from their bodies, is, that they remain in great fear and diſquietneſs, attending the puniſhment that is prepared for them at the latter day.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:152745:41"/>
               <p>Fourthly, The Doctrine of Purgatory condemneth the practice of all Chriſtian Churches: For it cannot be but an exceeding great breach of duty in them all (but eſpecially in thoſe that believe the ſouls of the dead may be benefitted by the prayers of the living) if they do not pray for the ſouls therein: for this is not to do by others, as they would have others to do by them; and therefore is againſt both the Law and Prophets, and directly oppoſite to the Command of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And that this is the continual practice of all Chriſtian Churches, is manifeſt; for the <hi>Greek,</hi> and all other <hi>Eastern</hi> Churches, notwithſtanding they daily pray for the dead, yet they never pray for the ſouls in Purgatory, for indeed they believe there is no Purgatory; but the prayers they offer up for the dead, are, that they may be ſaved at the Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> although it pray daily for the ſouls departed, yet it never prayeth for the ſouls in Purgatory, nor once craveth their deliverance thence.</p>
               <p>And although this may ſeem ſtrange, in regard of the many Maſſes ſhe daily (by her Prieſts) undertaketh to ſay for the ſouls therein, yet if we conſider the reaſon, 'tis no wonder at all: for when the prayers uſed in her ſaid Maſſes were firſt hatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhe did not believe of her now Purgatory, but the belief thereof (through the great profit ſhe perceived might thereby accrue to her Pope and Clergy) hath been infuſed into her fancy ſince. And to the end the ſame may appear truth, to wit, that ſhe prayeth not at all for the ſouls in Purgatory, I ſhall here give you an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the prayers ſhe at any time uſeth for the ſouls departed.</p>
               <p>The firſt of which is a very fooliſh prayer, in the Canon of her common Maſs, the which is this; <hi>Memento etiam, Domine, Famulorum &amp; Famularum tuarum</hi> (here is made a particular mention of certain particular dead Folks, whom it pleaſeth the Prieſt to name, and after is added) <hi>qui nos praeceſſerunt cum ſigno fidei, &amp; dormiunt in ſomno pacis,</hi> &amp;c. Remember, O Lord, thy Servants and Handmaids that have gone before us with the ſign of Faith, and ſleep in the ſleep of Peace. To theſe, O Lord, and to all thoſe that reſt in Chriſt, we pray thee that thou wilt grant place of comfort, of light and peace, through the ſame Chriſt our Lord, <hi>Amen.</hi> I call this prayer fooliſh, becauſe it ſpeaketh againſt it ſelf: For firſt it confeſſeth, that the dead do ſleep in the ſleep of Peace, and that they reſt in Chriſt; and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding afterward it deſireth that God would give them place of comfort, of light and peace; For if they ſleep in the ſleep of Peace, and reſt in Chriſt, have they not the place of peace? What need is there to ask that thoſe that ſleep in peace, ſhould have the place of peace? Is it not all one to ſleep in peace, and to have the place of peace? to reſt in Chriſt, and to have the place of comfort? If ſouls be tormented in Purgatory, yet they are not dead in their torment there; how therefore can they be ſaid to reſt: Peradventure the Defenders of the Canon of the Maſs will anſwer, that this prayer ſpeaketh of the body, when it ſaith, that the dead ſleep, and not of the ſoul. Well, ſuppoſe it do; for the ſoul indeed ſleepeth not, but only the body: but it ſaith alſo, that they have quietneſs and reſt; which ſpeech cannot well be underſtood of the body, but of that part that may be troubled; for what reſt can it be, to reſt in that part that can feel no manner of thing without the ſoul; and to be troubled in that part which, indeed, feeleth and liveth? When they ſay in their ſervice for the dead, <hi>Requieſcant in pace,</hi> let them reſt in peace, doubtleſs they mean to ſpeak of the ſoul, and not of the body; foraſmuch as there is no need to pray that the body of the dead ſhould reſt, becauſe that of neceſſity it doth reſt; but the ſoul may (as they think) have trouble and pain in Purgatory;
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:152745:42"/>and therefore they pray that they may have reſt, as concerning the foul. S. <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Apocalypſe,</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord:</hi> Why doth the Spirit ſay, <hi>that from henceforth they reſt from their labours?</hi> Will we ſay, that he ſpeaketh there of the reſt of the body, and not of the ſoul? If he ſpeak of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; what Prerogative have the bodies of the Juſt until the day of Judgment, more than the bodies of the Wicked, ſince the one and other would reſt equally, and there would be no difference in this point? And yet S. <hi>John</hi> maketh a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, for he calleth them the <hi>Dead in the Lord;</hi> that is to ſay, the <hi>Juſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> And why bleſſed? becauſe that from henceforth they ſhall reſt from their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and be in quiet; giving to underſtand, that the other do not reſt from their labour, but have more than ever they had, becauſe they be damned to everlaſting pain. So that when the reſt of the Juſt is ſpoken of, there is meant the reſt of the ſoul, and not of the body. Being then thus, that this prayer in the one part af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth that the Juſt ſleep in peace, and reſt in Chriſt, and in the other part deſireth that God would give them a place of peace and comfort, it plainly appeareth, that this prayer ſpeaketh againſt it ſelf, and is abſurd and fooliſh. But to return to the matter in hand in the ſaid prayer, you ſee, is no mention at all of the ſouls that broil in Purgatory, but of the ſouls that ſleep in peace, and reſt in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The ſecond prayer by which ſhe prayeth for the ſouls departed, is a prayer in her Maſs for the dead; and the ſame deſireth, that the ſoul of the Man or Woman de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted (to wit, for whom it prayeth) may not be given into the hands of the Enemy, but be received by the holy Angels, and carried into the Country of Paradiſe; to the end that having believed and hoped it may not ſuffer everlaſting pain, but poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs everlaſting joys.</p>
               <p>But here ſhe neither ſpeaketh of the pains of Purgatory, nor prayeth for the ſouls in Purgatory, for ſuch a requeſt doth not agree with the pains of Purgatory; for the pains of Purgatory (they ſay) are temporal, but the pains mentioned in this prayer are eternal? Neither doth it agree with the ſouls in Purgatory, for the ſouls in Purgatory ſhe will have to be ſuch as departed this World in the ſtate of Grace, which (as ſhe granteth her ſelf) are neither in peril, nor poſſibility of ſuffering e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal pain; whereas the ſouls prayed for here (as the prayer it ſelf giveth us to underſtand) are ſuch as are ſubject and liable to eternal damnation, for it prayeth they may not be given into the hands of the Enemy, nor ſuffer everlaſting pain.</p>
               <p>The third prayer with which ſhe prayeth for the ſouls departed, is alſo in her Maſs for the Dead, and is commonly called the <hi>Offertory,</hi> the which is as followeth: <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Jeſu Christe, Rex gloriae, libera animas omnium fidelium defunctorum, de ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu inferni, &amp; de profundo lacu, libera eas de ore leonis, ne abſorbeat eas tartarus, ſed ſignifer S.</hi> Michael <hi>repraeſentet eas in lucem ſanctam, &amp;c.</hi> O Lord Jeſus Chriſt, King of Glory, deliver the ſouls of all faithful dead, from the pains of Hell, and from the deep Lake, deliver them from the mouth of the Lyon, that Hell may not ſwallow them up, but that thy Standard-Bearer S. <hi>Michael</hi> may preſent them in the holy Light, the which in time paſt thou didſt promiſe to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed.</p>
               <p>But in this <hi>Offertory,</hi> you ſee, there is not a word ſpoke of Purgatory, but of Hell, and the deep Lake, and the Mouth of the Lyon; all which cannot agree with Purgatory, but with the place of the damned. Likewiſe the ſouls here ſpoke of, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the ſouls in Purgatory, for they (as ſhe holdeth her ſelf) are not in the leaſt danger of being ſwallowed up into Hell; however ſo far therein, but that S <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi> their Standard-Bearer (as ſhe calleth him) may be able to preſent them (when
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:152745:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>it ſhall pleaſe God) into the holy light: but this prayer deſireth, that the ſouls it prayeth for, may not be ſwallowed up into Hell, and in ſuch ſort, but that S. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi> their Standard-bearer may preſent them into the holy light.</p>
               <p>Her other prayers for the Souls departed, are certain Ejaculations; to wit, <hi>Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium animae per miſericordiam Dei requieſcant in Pace.</hi> Let the faithful Souls by the mercy of God reſt in peace. <hi>Requiem aeternam dona eis domine.</hi> Give them, O Lord, eternal reſt. <hi>A Porta inferi erue Domine animas corum.</hi> Deliver their Souls, O Lord, from the gates of Hell.</p>
               <p>But in theſe Ejaculations alſo, there is no mention at all, either of Purgatory, or of the Souls in Purgatory; and beſides the Ejaculations alſo are needleſs: For as for the reſt here ſpoke of, (She acknowledgeth in the aforeſaid Prayer in the Canon of her common Maſs) they have the ſame already; and as for the Gates of Hell they never enter them. But ſuppoſe they did enter them, out of Hell there is no redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo ſhe prayeth in vain. This latter alſo, and moreover the two prayers before mentioned in the Maſs for the dead, are no better than blaſphemous; for they give us to underſtand, that the Souls of the Faithful departed this life, may be damned in Hell; and that, to all Eternity.</p>
               <p n="15">15ly. The Doctrine of Purgatory robbeth God of his Juſtice. For ſince the ſins of the Faithful are ſufficiently ſatisfied for by the Death of Chriſt, ſince God in him forgiveth them; and ſince all ſuch Souls as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> would have in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, are (as ſhe affirmeth her ſelf) void of fault; having (as ſhe faith) all their guiltineſs firſt taken away, and the ſame forgiven them here in this world: It follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth neceſſarily, that if God puniſh them, (and Purgatory the Papiſts ſay is a place for that purpoſe) he puniſheth Souls that are no longer guilty, taketh venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of ſins that are already pardoned, and exacts debts that are already paid, taking two payments for one and the ſelf ſame debt, and two ſatisfactions for one and the ſelf ſame ſin, to wit, the Paſſion of Chriſt, and the pains of Purgatory, and this notwithſtanding the firſt was intire. 'Twould be very unjuſt for us, to deal thus with our enemies; how much more then for God to deal thus with his Children.</p>
               <p n="6">6ly. The Doctrine of Purgatory maketh God a mocker; for God would abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mock us, did he but ſa to us as the Doctrine of Purgatory would have him; to wit, I will forgive thee, but yet I will puniſh thee. I forgive thee thy debt, but thou ſhalt pay me. For our ſins are debts, the payment whereof is the puniſhment.</p>
               <p>In fine, we need not go any further to confute the Doctrine of Purgatory, than to the Romaniſts own Tenents. For if the Pope be infallible, as the Romaniſts hold and affirm he is. Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt, in his 13. Book upon <hi>Job, Chap.</hi> 20. telleth us plainly, that <hi>Quia authoris noſtri gratia redempti ſumus, hoc jam coeleſtis muneris habemus, ut cum de carnis noſtra habitatione ſubtrahimur, mox ad coeleſtia premia ducamur.</hi> Becauſe we are redeemed by the grace of our Creator, we have this heavenly gift, that when our Souls depart out of this fleſhly habitation, we are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently carried to the heavenly rewards. Likewiſe, if the Book of Wiſdom be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical, as they hold it is, and the Souls in Purgatory be the Souls of the Righteous, as they alſo hold; the ſame is as clear and as evident a teſtimony againſt it as may be. For 'tis ſaid there, <hi>The Souls of the Righteous are in the hands of God, there ſhall no Torment touch them,</hi> Wiſ. 3.6.</p>
               <p>The Papiſts alledge certain places of holy Scripture, to prove their pretended Purgatory, but againſt their true ſence.</p>
               <p>Firſt they alledge <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.32. where Chriſt ſpeaking of the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, ſaith; <hi>It ſhall nor be forgiven in this world, nor in the world to come.</hi> And thereby they would imply, that ſome ſins ſhall be forgiven in the world to come, which they ſay is, Purgatory.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:152745:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>But Purgatory cannot be ſaid to be the world to come, becauſe (as they ſay) 'tis already in being. Beſides Purgatory (they ſay is) is a place of torment and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and not of pardon: And moreover (according to their own Doctrine) ſin is pardoned before the Souls enter into Purgatory. The ſence of this place is as clear as may be. Not to pardon ſin, is to puniſh it. And Jeſus Chriſt declareth, that God will puniſh the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt, both in this life, and at the day of Judgment, which in <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.35. is called the other world.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. They alledge <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.58, 59 where 'tis ſaid, <hi>Whilſt thou goest with thine Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary to the Magiſtrate, as thou art in the way, give diligence that thou mayest be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from him, leſt he draw thee to the Judge, and the Judge deliver thee to the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, and the Officer cast thee into Priſon. I tell thee, thou ſhalt not come out thence, till thou haſt paid the very utmost Mite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Way they would have to ſignify Life the Magiſtrate God, the Priſon the Fire of Purgatory, the Officer they know not who, and the Adverſary the Devil; and ſo by conſequence they would have us to agree with the Devil: And that we are in the way with the Devil; For S. <hi>Mathew</hi> ſpeaking of this ſame paſſage, rendereth it thus, <hi>Agree with thine Adverſary quickly, whilſt thou art in the way with him,</hi> Mat. 5.25. For theſe very reaſons, ſome of them would have the Devil to be the Sergeant and the Law the Adverſary; but this mendeth not the matter at all but maketh it worſe. For doth the Devil draw the faithful into Purgatory? are we in the way with the Law? Is the Law of God our Enemy? are we to ſeek means to deliver our ſelves from it, and to ſhake off its yoke? for 'tis ſaid here, that we muſt give diligence in the way, that we may be delivered from the Adverſary. And if this Priſon be Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and Souls muſt ſtay therein till ſuch times they have paid the very utmoſt mite, how cometh it to paſs that the Pope by Indulgences may deliver them out from thence before.</p>
               <p>But this their comment is a meer Fiction, and is not the ſence of this place of Scripture. Chriſt here exhorteth us to peace and Unity, and would not have us to ſtrive and contend one with another in law This is affirmed by S <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> who in his expoſition hereupon, ſaith; that Chriſt ſpeaketh here, <hi>De reconciliand a pace diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidentium Fratrum.</hi> Of making peace between Brethren at ſtrife.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly. They Alledge 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11, 12, 13, 14, 15. where 'tis ſaid no other Foundation can any man ſay than that which is laid, which is Jeſus Chriſt. And if any man build on this Foundation, Gold, Silver, precious ſtones, Timber, Hay, or Stubble; every mans work ſhall be made manifeſt, for the day ſhall diſcover it, becauſe it ſhall be reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by fire; and the fire ſhall try every mans work of what ſort it is; if any mans work abide which he hath built thereupon, he ſhall receive wages; if any mans work burn, he ſhall ſuffer loſs; but he ſhall be ſaved himſelf, yet ſo as it were by fire.</p>
               <p>The fire that is here ſpoke of, they would have to be the fire of Purgatory: but this cannot be for the fire mentioned here, doth not agree with the fire of Purgatory. For the fire of Purgatory (they ſay) burneth and puniſheth the Soul, but this burneth and tryeth the works. The fire of Purgatory (they ſay) is real, but this is only comparative for tis ſaid here, he ſhall be ſaved, yet ſo as it were by fire. Moreover from the fire of Purgatory (they ſay) are exempted Martyrs; but from this are exempted none, for 'tis ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>wiſe here, it ſhall try every mans works.</p>
               <p>As for the ſenſe of this place of Scripture, the day that is here ſpoke of, is the courſe of time we have to ſpend here in this life: Of which S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2. ſaith, <hi>Behold, now is the accepted time: Behold now is the day of Salvation.</hi> And the fire that is here mentioned, is the heat of affliction, Perſecution, and trouble we ſuffer in which courſe of time; of which S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5, 6, 7. ſaith, <hi>We are kept by the Power of God through Faith unto Salvation, ready to be revealed in the laſt time:
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:152745:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>wherein we greatly rejoice, though now for a ſeaſon (if need be) we are in heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs through manifold temptations; that the tryal of our Faith being much more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious than of gold that periſheth, though it be tryed by fire, might be found unto praiſe, and honour, and glory, at the appearing of Jeſus Christ.</hi> And again, 1 Pet. 4.12, 13. <hi>My beloved, account not your fiery tryal as though it were ſome strange thing happened to you, but as you are partakers of Chriſts ſufferings rejoyce, that in the Revelation of his Glory you may triumphing be glad</hi> And Chriſt ſpeaking of the ſame, compareth their heat to the ſcorching heat of the Sun. This place of S. <hi>Paul</hi> is thus alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his Manual to <hi>Laurentius, Chap.</hi> 68.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, They alledge, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.27. where the Spirit of God ſpeaking of the Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſaith, <hi>There ſhall enter into it no unclean thing.</hi> From whence they infer, there muſt needs be a Purgatory. But this maketh nothing at all for them; for he ſpeaketh here (as the words following declare) of the prophane and wicked, ſuch as are not written in the Book of Life, but ſhall be caſt into Hell: Beſides, as for others, they may not be ſaid unclean, for they are purged and cleanſed in the Blood of Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, They alledge 2 <hi>Mac.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. where <hi>Judas Macchabeus</hi> cauſed Sacrifices to be offered for the dead: but this maketh rather againſt Purgatory, than for it; for the Author of the Book teſtifieth, that what <hi>Judas</hi> therein did, had reſpect to the Reſurrection, and was that they might riſe again to Salvation, and not that they might be taken out from the ſire of Purgatory. Moreover, this Book is <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> for it is not found in the Original of the Old Teſtament, which is the Hebrew Bible; wherefore neither Jeſus Chriſt, nor any of his Apoſtles, did ever quote the Books of the <hi>Macchabees,</hi> or any other of the <hi>Apocrypha:</hi> The Author himſelf ſays, that his intention in this Book is to make an abridgment of the Hiſtory of <hi>Jaſon</hi> the <hi>Cyre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian:</hi> And ſhall the abridgment of a Hiſtory be accounted Canonical, when the Hiſtory it ſelf was not Canonical? How therefore can it be ſufficient whereupon to ground any point of Doctrine appertaining to our Faith? Alſo the Author, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the end of his Book, doubteth whether he hath ſaid well or no, and ſays, by way of excuſe, that he hath done it as well as he could. This cannot be the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Spirit of God, for it neither doubteth of its well doing, nor excuſeth its ſelf to men; and therefore the Doctrine of Purgatory may not be grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this place. Beſides, the <hi>Greeks</hi> do as much as what is mentioned here, and yet they utterly deny Purgatory. And S. <hi>Augustine</hi> in his Book of the care for the Dead, approveth prayer for the Dead, and yet in all that Book ſpeaketh not one word of Purgatory.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Rather than they will have Purgatory utterly overthrown, they bring in S. <hi>Auguſtine, lib.</hi> 21. <hi>cap.</hi> 26. <hi>de Civitate Dei,</hi> doubting whether or no, after this life, there be any ſuch thing as a purging fire; and thereby they imply, that there may be ſuch a place as Purgatory. But this maketh nothing for them neither; for the fire that S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> there doubteth of, is the fire that was held by moſt of the Fathers ſhould be immediately after the Reſurrection, when Chriſt cometh to judge the World,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Lactan. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> in which they believed that every mans works ſhould be tryed, which they call a Baptiſm of Fire, from which they exempt no man, no not ſo much as the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ambroſ. Serm. <hi>20.</hi> ſup. Pſal. <hi>118.</hi>
                  </note> Apoſtles, or the Virgin<note n="(c)" place="margin">Hilar. ſup Pſal. <hi>119.</hi> in Par. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Mary;</hi> but the Purgatory which the <hi>Papiſt</hi> dream of, they ſay is now in being, and endeth at the day of Judgment; and moreover, is not for all, but for certain perſons which they by have not here fully ſatisfied Gods Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice for their ſins; which Purgatory S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> putteth us out of doubt of, (though he doubts of the other) ſaying;<note n="(d)" place="margin">Aug. l. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> c. <hi>16.</hi> de Civit. Dei.</note> 
                  <hi>Purgatorias autem panas nullas futures opinatur, niſi ante illud ultimum tremendumque judicium.</hi> Unleſs, as 'tis thought at the laſt Iudgment, after this life there are no purging pains.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:152745:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Wherein is ſhewed, that could a man ſatisfie (as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay) beyond Gods Juſtice, or the deſert of his ſins, yet thoſe ſatisfactions ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abounding, may not be given (as they pretend) to others.</head>
               <p>NOne but Chriſt could ever ſatisfie (through payment and recompence to God) the Divine Juſtice for ſins: As for others, the beſt of us all are unable (as I have ſhewed before) thus to ſatisfie for them, yea for our own ſins, much leſs alſo for the ſins of others. The Doctrine of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> which teacheth that a man may thus ſatisfie, not only for himſelf, but withall have an overplus wherewith to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate and ſatisfie for others, and which the Pope may apply to others, is a meer Prodigy, a benefit which hath never yet accrewed to us, or ever hereafter ſhall accrew to us, by any (even the greateſt) of Chriſts Saints: For if any of them ſhould ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thus for others, it would follow, that Chriſt is not alone our Saviour, and this is manifeſtly falſe, for there is no Salvation in any other, neither is there any other Name given under Heaven whereby we muſt be ſaved, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.12. Nevertheleſs ſhould or could they do it, and did they undertake it, 'twould not be accepted of; for every man (as the Scripture ſaith) ſhall bear his own burthen, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.5. Every man ſhall receive his own reward according to his own labour, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.8. And a man can by no means redeem his Brother, or pay a Ranſom to God for him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.7 What a bold preſumption is it therefore for the <hi>Papiſts</hi> to go about to perſwade us, that God will accept the Faſtings, Whippings, and Pilgrimages of S. <hi>Bennet,</hi> or S. <hi>Francis,</hi> in payment of the puniſhment due to the ſins of others: Beſides it is needleſs, for the ſatisfaction of Jeſus Chriſt is ſufficient for us, without an addition of the Whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings of the Saints. It is likewiſe to accuſe God of injuſtice, to think that he hath ſent any one more ſufferings than his ſins have deſerved; and is alſo to take the height of ſin amiſs, not knowing how great puniſhments are due to it, ſince our Saviour Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall ſay unto his Brother, thou Fool, ſhall be in danger of Hell Fire.</hi> Moreover, it is a meer mocking of the Saints, to ſet them to do that which is already done.</p>
               <p>As for the Pope, he need not ſo much concern himſelf, to take ſouls from Purgatory which are not there: But ſuppoſe they were there, ſince they are the ſouls of the faithful, for which Chriſt intercedeth with his Father, and that continually, how cometh it to paſs that they come not out from thence at Chriſts Interceſſions, and yet come out at the Popes Pardons? Beſides, what doth the Pope in this his taking out of ſouls from Purgatory, but exalt himſelf above God? for if it be Gods Will to puniſh his Children in a fire, why will not the Pope ſuffer him to puniſh them as it pleaſeth him? Moreover, 'tis plain, that if the Pope will needleſly take ſouls from Purgatory, he doth it without Authority, for the Power of the Keys (by which he pretends to do the ſame) extendeth not to the Dead; for if Chriſt thereby gave him power to unbind and unlooſe upon Earth, yet he gave him not the power of looſing under the Earth. If alſo (according to the Romaniſts own Doctrine) ſatisfactions be meritorious, and a man muſt firſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit here on Earth what he afterwards hath in Heaven, and cannot merit here ſo much, but he may have a reward there to equalize it; what an unjuſt thing is it for the Pope, when a Monk or Fryer having watched, faſted, whipped, trotted to Rome, yea it may be to Jeruſalem, on Pilgrimage, and this to obtain a more than a common reward in Heaven, is no ſooner got to Heaven, but he is diveſted of all his ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abundant Merits, and is forced to take up there with what place the Pope (though on Earth) is pleaſed to leave and appoint him, and to admit a ſtranger (in ſome reſpects it may be to God himſelf) to enjoy the fruits of his travel. Moreover, what an unjuſt thing (if he have ſuch power) is it in him, to tye the remiſſion of ſins to certain places? So that although a man ſhould do ten times the Devotion elſewhere, yet he ſhould not have the ſame Pardon. I would fain know of the Romaniſts, who hath put the Saints ſuperabundant ſufferings into their Churches Treſſury? who gave the ſame into the Popes Cuſtody? when and where this diſtribution did firſt begin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> how we ſhall be aſſured that God will take the ſame for current payment? wherefore the Chief Prelates, mentioned in the Old Teſtament, had not ſuch Treaſuries wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the ſufferings of Noah, Abraham, and Moſes? wherefore Chriſt and his Apoſtles did forget to ſpeak of this Treaſure? and why they ſuffered ſuch ſurpluſage to be loſt by ill Husbandry? or what ſhall become of the many thouſand years Indulgences which a man may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain more than he hath need of? Certainly theſe Indulgences are moſt horrible Pollutions, whereby the Church of Rome is moſt naſtily corrupted.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
